Foreword
(For the Third Edition)

Many great souls have encouraged this book. I express my grateful thanks to them.

Even after the copies of the previous edition have been exhausted the demands for this book have been received. After expressing my sorrow for not being able to provide copies, I beg their pardon.

For various reasons the printing work got delayed for this edition.

It has been possible for two new episodes to be added in this edition.

Similarly, the important names of the individuals have been incorporated in the alphabetical order and those of the citations.

Sri C. Krishna and Sri S.R. Ramaswamy have whole-heartedly helped in correcting the proofs.

I have given a lot of trouble to Sri. K. Chidambaram in preparing this book for printing. With his natural friendliness and affection he has borne all difficulties and has helped.

Bangalore
July 1969

DVG

Foreword
(For the Second edition)

This lecture seems to have met with the approval of the general public. The book reviews have also been in accordance. I thank all of them.

The Mysore University has accepted this as a Text Book for the B.A. and B.Sc. classes for the year 1957.

In the opportunity obtained this for re-printing it has been enlarged a little. Since some people suggested that at times the sentences are very cryptic and epigrammatic, in such places one or two words have been added.

A Radio-talk “Samskriti – Prakriti” (Culture and Nature) which is a new chapter here was printed in our prominent newspapers. It has earned me enthusiastic responses from various sources. Again, my thanks.

I believe that in the present expanded version the work will fulfil its objective even better.

Bangalore
June 22, 1956.

DVG

Foreword
(For the First edition)

In this lecture some complex issues like Truth, Dharma and Progress have been discussed. Its length has already exceeded the intended limit. Therefore many aspects of those subjects could not be commented on here. There is an intention to write a different lecture on those topics. The explanation of some of the topics dealt with in this lecture are found in the present writer’s books “Rajya Sastra”.

DVG

Culture - A preface

A Preface

The word “Culture” has come into use greatly in recent times. It may be said that the main reason for this is because the word “Culture” in English is being used a lot and has gained currency in modern usage.

The word “Culture” in English in today’s context and meaning is being used since about a hundred years. Its use has attained additional significance especially in the last fifty years, gradually. After the United Nations was born (1945) the use of this word is abundant. In 1946, when the UNESCO was formed, the word “Culture” was incorporated in its very name and gave it an authoritative place. The Indian Government has hoisted the flag of culture.

Then what is the meaning of this word which has such an influential position?

Nobody has yet authoritatively defined the meaning of the word. In parlance, there are many loose meanings. A society of scholars has not brought it to a conclusive stage. If you look at the history of such a society, in its discussion of this question, instead of solving the question, it looks as though a fresh generation has got an argument to contend with.

Some people may feel that the special feature of culture is that it has not come under any restriction. Since it has remained so “shapeless” anybody can use it in any situation to complete a sentence. When at the beginning of a lecture when a word or idea with a definite specific meaning does not suggest itself, the lecturer when he brings forth “Culture”, the audience (or the readers) get the impression that something profound is being said. By the very word “Culture” the ear hears something of importance. Culture, Freedom, Equality, Fraternity, Dharma – etc. are the terminology of creating impressiveness. The meaning of these words can be expanded or contracted at will and an indescribable aura can be brought about. Such clichés are the saving friends of a speech-maker. When there is no other helper, these are of use.

Nobody will say that the word “Culture” has no meaning. Not only does it have a meaning; but its meaning is very extensive, many faceted and very important for our lives. Though no authoritative statement or a definitive dictionary give an explanation of its meaning, we can understand the meaning of that word through its use by the learned people. The meaning of so many quintessential words which are in our daily use cannot be easily explained in precise terminology. What is “Man”? What is “Truth”? What is “Dharma”? These questions are easily asked but difficult to be answered. We can recognize the animal called Man. We can point it out by our finger. But difficult to explain in so many words. Still there are answers. To get to know them is possible by effort. Let us find out by consideration and discussion.

Etymology

While discussing the influence of education or while talking about the good nature and conduct of cultivated people, the word “Culture” makes its appearance as an adjunct. This word does not seem to have been in use in ancient works. But its related synonym “Samskara” is in early use. Expressions like “Sixteen Samskaras”, the “Samskara” of intellect etc. are familiar to everyone. The language which has “samskara” is “Samskrita”. Similarly the man who has a sound educational training is a “Samskrita”. This is the past usage.

The wealth of good qualities of a “Samskrita” is “Samskriti”. In this sense, the word “Samskriti” is coming into increased use in Kannada now for the past fifteen to twenty years. This is an essential word. When a new word is coming into use among us, it means that a new idea is entering into our life. A new word for a new idea or feeling. Actually rather than calling it a new feeling, it is better to think of it as a revived idea. Now it is coming into memory; something old which had gone out of sight is coming back with a shine and a new resplendence. This shows the animation of that object. That being the case it is essential to the fulfillment of our life.

That quality or characteristic of man which we are proclaiming as “Samskriti”, in this sense the English word “Culture” has also come into common parlance only recently – since about a hundred and fifty years. The origin of the word culture is “Cult” or “Cultus” in Latin. The original meaning of the word was along the lines of “elevated”, “enlightened”, “show respect”, “serve”, “refinement”, “development”, “improvement”, “dedication” and such – from this gradually arose two meanings– (1) “theism” – acceptance of religious belief, etc. (2) the worship of the earth, interest in land, agriculture, cultivation, etc. From the second meaning came “Agriculture”. Gradually, from this came cultivation of land, growing produce and words like “horticulture” (gardening), arboriculture (growing trees and bushes), etc. Further along came “sericulture” (rearing silk worms), “pissiculture” (fisheries) and words like that. By keeping on expanding, the study of bacteria gave raise to “bacteriological culture” and the meaning – manufacture of artificial pearls, etc. In recent times, especially in America, the word refers to the social organizations of various races, the matrimonial and other forms of practices, the conduct of the family, the customs and manners of eating and etiquette modes of social behaviour and the style of living came to be referred to. About a hundred years ago (1867) “Culture” came to signify a man’s intellectual cultivation, the superiority of the mind and the inner development. Thus “Culture” has come to signify the sophistication and refinement attained through literature, music, painting, sculpture and such other arts. This superior artistic temperament came to be known as “Culture”. Now about eighty years ago (1869), the English scholar – poet, Mathew Arnold, in his lengthy essay “Culture and Anarchy” has discussed the mental attitudes and propensities of three classes of people in the English society of that time which appeared prominent to him. (1) those who are born rich are “barbarians”. (2) the middle-class people who are interested in money – matters and bodily comforts are the “philistines”. (3) The poor people who are busy in day-to- day existence are the “populace”. Arnold’s complaint is that in none of these three is found the taste for culture as all these were not supporters of spiritual values. Let us look at Bhartrihari’s statement.

Culture is not mere education, it is the pollen of the flower of education. It is a totally satisfying conduct and character born out of the wedlock of literary sensibility and discrimination of worldly wisdom; it is the sum total or the end product of the comparative knowledge of various subjects, various aspirations and goods, various philosophical standpoints, and various religious beliefs. That is the gentle and sophisticated softness, good behaviour and respectful attitude of culture.

Culture is not mere scholarship. A man may learn a dozen languages; may have read hundreds of books; he may have at his finger tips grammars and dictionaries. But by only this he cannot be considered a “Cultured” person.

Culture is not mere knowledge or the mastery over scientific information about physical things and substances. A man may have traveled in many countries; he may have transacted business with hundreds of people. He may have put into his store – house of memory information of a thousand things collected from various sources like books on geography, history, government reports and newspapers. But this collection, by itself cannot become “Culture”.

Mere cleverness and shrewdness is not “Culture” either. A man may converse with astonishing wit, he may be an expert in logic and make his opponent accept defeat by using ingenious arguments. Being careful and patient in carrying out works with planning and smoothness, one can win victory. Even this is not culture.

Music and such other taste for art which are learnt is not culture. A man may identify various ragas; one can criticize the strength and weakness of the strokes of a painting; one can discuss the proportions of a sculptural piece; one can be an expert actor. From these things one can not prove that he is cultured.

He may be good speaker, may have mastery of speech, he may cite poetry and proverbs in conversation; he may narrate anecdotes, he may show dexterity in dialogue; None of these constitute the inner core of culture.

Then, what is Culture? From refinement comes culture. Refinement or ‘Samskarana’ – ‘Samyak Karana’ – “Samyak Kriti” comes “Samskriti” or culture, which means doing well, making something beautiful, refining something, cleaning of something and making it good. “Good” means a substance or subject matter is the way it should be. That is “Good” when the ultimate goal of life is brought closer in an object or behaviour, that is pleasing and convenient. That is, propriety. That is, genuineness. The effort to find that “Good” – the search for that beauty, that truth is culture. The means and method by which what is pleasant and meaningful is brought into our lives, this method is culture. In our various contacts and interactions with the world, the propriety that we create is culture.

Isn’t beauty a condition, a state, that everybody desires everywhere? We wash ourselves and bedeck ourselves with ornaments. We get our houses painted. We search for beauty for whatever we see. Similarly don’t we need certain elegance in our worldly relationships? Those behavioural patterns are culture. It is the beauty of feeling, a beauty of conduct. That living creature who doesn’t wear that ornament is a forest animal. Just as we try to make our home and health clean, so must we consciously strive to make our relationship with the world beautiful. This alone is the sum total of culture.

The orderly cleanliness of word and deed is culture. Cleanliness means taking out all dirt. So the work of culture is rubbing off the dirt of the mind and washing it away.

The discrimination between right and wrong, the suitable and the unsuitable in our daily situations is an aspect of culture; Another aspect is judging the value of things and their priorities; yet another aspect is the awareness of other people’s aims and intentions; another aspect is taste in simplicity; yet another is awareness of the stabilizing force of Dharma / right conduct. Another aspect is the soul – searching self realization. Thus culture is the result of the integration resulting in bringing together disparate kinds of knowledge and different kinds of disciplines.

This achievement of the fruition of life is through inner cultivation. The different facets of this cultivation are – study of books, dedication to the arts and the company of Connoisseurs There is no opposition between scholarship and culture. There is no enmity between sharpness of mind and culture. There is place in culture for scholarship, brilliance and sharpness of intellect. But this by itself cannot constitute culture. Culture is the end product of the inner consciousness. This product requires several ingredients. No one of these can call itself culture by itself.

Culture and Progress – both these words have the same intention originally. The superior life – that great concept holds up each side through each word. That which – improves life is culture; that which leads to improvement is progress. In ordinary parlance, the purification of the inner being is culture – the dexterity of morality, ethics, finesse and efficiency. Progress consists of the methodical, proper working for the intended goal and purpose, in bringing about comfort, convenience and wealth. Primarily, culture belongs to the individual, progress to the society.

Both these concepts are contained in Dharma – Dharma is holding together bearing and wearing. That is Dharma which valuable life is wearing. What is it that which is the adhesive integrating force? It is that unchanging, Eternal Entity which has three components – (1) The individual or self (2) The surrounding world which appears (3) Iswara or God or the Lord.

Each entity or substance in creation has a special quality or characteristic of its own – coldness for water, movement for the air, the burning heat for fire, flight for the bird, thoughtfulness for man. Thus each individuality or natural and true remembrance of the lord of the universe, for the sake of attaining a vision of Him through co-operating with the life of the universe through the flowering forth of natural and authentic quality – that is Dharma.

One face of Dharma is the Philosophy that promotes spiritual progress; the other face, the knowledge of science which makes for worldly progress; yet another face is the fine – art of living; - culture.

The Words of Mathew Arnold

Let us listen to the words of Mathew Arnold, an experienced person in this field. The attempt to make every situation in life, relevant, proper and meaningful through our attitude and action is culture. He says –

‘‘Culture’’ moves inspired not merely by the desire of purely scientifically discriminatory understanding of information of the mind, but it is also inspired by the strong force of social welfare and the desire for right conduct and beliefs.’’ According to Bishop Wilson, the defining sentence reads –

‘Making Wisdom and the will of God strong in the World’.

A delicate aspect should not be forgotten here. It is possible that while in our enthusiasm to do good and examining what is God’s will, we may lose our caution and be misled. When our desire for the good is keen, our mind will be action bound. Then we will not have enough patience to give enough attention to the critical examination of the subject. Therefore whatever our mind sees as relevant, we carry out in action these half-baked immature ideas. But this is not a characteristic of Culture. In culture, in addition to the desire to do good, the desire for knowledge is also intermixed. What is wisdom? What is the will of God? Culture requires a sound understanding in these matters. It cannot tolerate un-researched ideas. Culture accepts the fact that any action, any arrangement cannot last and cannot be beneficial unless it has the foundation of discriminatory knowledge as well as the will of God. That is why, even in the most sacred ideal of correcting the mistakes and shortcomings of the world and problems solved, culture cannot act in haste. True culture recognizes that without knowing correctly what the right action is and what is salutary the work undertaken may result in disaster.

“Culture is a by-product of social life. A man who lives alone by himself cannot obtain its comprehensive and complete essence. It is a rule that an individual who is treading the path of this perfection has to take others along. If he breaks this rule, his progress will be impeded and his development itself is truncated and he becomes weak. He must constantly augment the group of his fellow travellers.

“The flowering forth of all the forces which value the beauty of human nature, their simultaneous commingling is culture. No one single force among them should dominate to the detriment of the others. Looked at this way, culture is broader than the injunctions of religion.’’

“We have, haven’t we, used the words complete propriety and complete conglomeration of good qualities above? Completeness means attainment of a certain ideal; it is not achieving something; it is not getting something. It is an inner state, an inner mental attitude. It is not external circumstances; it doesn’t conquer others; it is not the feeling of profit by defeating others.’’

“Culture is the alloy of good qualities. In this alloy of fullness, two excellent characteristics are combined – Sweetness and Light. Culture is equal to poetry. It has to follow the right path that poetry follows. The concept of a beautiful life and the attainment of the almond salubrious which brings it about – this is the main quality of poetry; so it is of culture”.

This is the view of Matthew Arnold We can accept this as a definition.

‘We have said that the word culture is new to Kannada. But the object suggested by this word is now new to us. It is as old as the Vedas, the Ramayana and the Mahabharata. The Mantras and the teachings used in the “Samskaras” (religious rituals) like the “Upanayana” (the initiation ceremony) show the quintessential nature of culture.

The Oath Taken at Upanayana

(I will act according to the rule of what should be remembered and what should be forgotten, what is to be eschewed and what is not, what is to be believed and what not to be believed, what is to be learned and what not – in all these dualities, in the matters of what is beneficial to human beings and with regard to prescribed duties; in all things pertaining to the highest state of the soul, in all these things, I will act following the relevant injunctions in each and everyone of the cases).

The Religious Duty of a Bachelor

(Unceasingly trying to keep all this activities under control) (Praising oneself denigrading others is to be eschewed)

- Apastamba

(He must be a teller of truth, one without shame and pride)

- Bodhayana.

The hero of Srimad Ramayana and Yudhishtira of Mahabharata are the ideal human beings exemplifying the acme of culture. When the English people, when they admire the speech and conduct of an individual, they call him a “gentleman”. In that one word are embedded the feelings of Honourable, Generous, Noble and Courteous. Similarly our words of praise are “Susamskrita, Sushikshita, Sabhya, Sajjana, Sadgrihasta, Maanishtha, Manyadevanta, Sambhavita, Doddamanushya”, etc. These indicate the nature of culture. Rama and Dharmaraja are gentlemen by birth.

Who is a “Gentleman?”

Cardinal Newman’s (an English man of Religion) description is famous.

“He is merely occupied in merely removing the obstacles which hinder the free and unembarrassed action of those about him. His great concern is to make everyone at ease and at home. He has his eyes on all his company, he is tender towards the bashful, gentle towards the distant and merciful towards the absurd. He is seldom prominent in conversations, and never wearisome. He makes light of favours which he does them, and seems to be receiving when he is conferring. He never speaks of himself except when compelled, never defends himself by a mere retort, he has no ears for slander or gossip, is scrupulous in imprinting motives to those who interfere with him and interprets everything for the best. From a long-sighted prudence, he observes the maxim of the ancient sage, that we should ever conduct ourselves towards our enemy as if he were one day to be our friend. He may be right or wrong in his opinion, but he is too clear-headed to be unjust; he is as simple as he is forcible and as brief as he is decisive”.

The Example of Valmiki

In the Ramayana, here and there the nature of the speech and expression of a cultured man is described. Among those incidents, the address of Hanuman on his first meeting Rama and Lakshmana is one. At Kishkindha, near the Rishyamuka mountain as soon as Hanuman sees Rama and Lakshmana, he takes the shape of an ascetic, introduces himself “I am the minister of Sugriva, praises their effulgent looks and bravery and asks “Who are the two of you? You look like Gods. What is the purpose of your visit here?” and so on. Rama praises the beauty of Hanuman’s speech in these words.

(This person has learnt his grammar well. Though he has spoken so much, there is not a single inappropriate word. The speech is not lengthy, still it doesn’t give room for any ambiguity. It is not slow, neither is it fast. The voice is not very loud, neither is it too soft and inaudible. It is of medium pace and pitch There is a pre-determined logical sequence in the presentation of the concerned matter. This auspicious speech which is neither too hasty or too tardy has an appeal to the heart and captures it).

If these words of Valmiki are compared with the above complementary sentences of Newman, the characteristics of the speech, emotion and expression of a cultured person shine forth in our mind.

The Summary Statement of Bhartrihari

The following stanza of the poet Bhartrihari tells about the essential characteristics of a cultured person briefly.

Observe this also

Culture is a sort of self-education. It is not just the workings of the mind or of the discriminatory faculty; Neither is it mere memory power. It belongs to that entity of individual self which is the master of the mind, the discriminatory faculty and memory. The wind combines into itself as one unified rich and strange unnamable synthetic perfume of variety of smells from variegated hundreds of forest flowers like champaka, kedage, jasmine, padari, suragi, honne, etc. The doctor dissolves into a single concoction the essence of several medicinal herbs and prepares a new panacea of liquid portion. Similarly, culture is the salubrious commingling of various emotions and feelings – a discipline – of a variety of music and other fine arts, disciplines and branches of learning. There is sense in it, wisdom in it, generosity in it, courage in it, hardness and laxity. Let us remember this sentence of Bhavabhuti –

(How can one fathom the heart of an exceptional person? It can be harder than a diamond. It can also be softer than a flower).

Valmiki has given an example for this:

Sri Rama is Vishnu in his valour; still he looks like the moon. When he is angry he is like the fire of deluge; but in forgiveness he is like Mother Earth).

What does this mean? The qualities that are required to make life meaningful are many, and not of one kind only. For a casual look they may look like mutually contradictory. But there is a method of integration and reconciling them; In that integrated state they become complementary.

Anger and Forgiveness are by nature opposite of each other like Fire and Water. But in great men they stay side by side. When he feels that anger is just, forgiveness recedes silently. When forgiveness is just, anger bows out. These various qualities get fulfilled only by the following of propriety. A good quality when it breaks its bounds, no matter how valuable by itself, at the time of the carrying out of action brings about only misfortune. This sort of propriety born out of discrimination and the manifestation of good which follows a sense of propriety is the characteristic of culture.

We said that culture means the achievement of propriety in the activity of living. We said that it is an agreeable amalgam of various qualities; we said that it is the discriminatory knowledge of various grades relationships and their complementary commingling. Which is the directing principle for that propriety? What is the ideal for this homogeneous state? In taking into account the differences, what is it that determines true value?

The Value System of the Stuff of Life

In the world when we want to determine the value of any object, we accept an universally recognized entity as its measure. When we measure time the winking of eyes (which is known as “nimisha” meaning minute) becomes the first measure. The stride of a foot for a foot or the mark on the finger for an inch become its measure. In weighing gold the red grain (gulaganji) becomes the measure. In measuring rice a handful becomes the measure. In counting money a paisa or some other small coin becomes the standard. Then what is the measure to determine the genuineness of culture? To determine the various ingredients to be mixed in proper proportions which is the balance that can take on the

correct weights? Which is the measuring rod to apply to proper and improper things?

Propriety is the highest point of good nature or state. We use freely words like good, soothing, auspicious and bringer of fortune and fame. But how to determine which is beneficial? What is its characteristic? What is its means of its attainment and its proof?

Our ancestors have delved deep into this question and have searched its source. Their conclusion is that what is permanent and everlasting is the good and beneficial.

In Sanskrit language ‘Sat’ means (1) that which is, and (2) that which is GOOD. In Kannada ‘OL’ (UL) means the same –(1) that which has formulated itself and (2) that which brings about good. That which can live or exist without destruction, that is the truly good.

From ‘Sat’ comes “Truth” (Satya). From ‘Sat’ comes Essence (Sattva).

Of all truths, the ultimate truth is the Self. That is the Supreme Soul (“Paramatma”) or “Parabrahman”. That is what is called God or “Bhagavan”. That is the entity which is Eternal, which remains the same at all times and in all states, which is unsublatable, unchanging, the same, ever-lasting, and always existing. That is why, in all our worldly activities and worldly glories what is close to the Eternal Entity and to what extent, to that extent, that particular thing is capable of doing good to us. What things take us away from the memory of the Supreme, they become un-enjoyable to us. Thus the vision of the Supreme is that which determines our means of measuring.

Of all the things that a man knows, his own inner being is the complete truth as far as he is concerned. Of all things, that which he knows first and foremost without any doubt is his own inner soul known to him as “I”, “I”, and the support for all this knowledge is this same consciousness, his soul. Life exists on account of it. The soul itself is Life. From this Soul is the world. Thus the individual soul is the source for the existence of man. That is the beginning of his life; that is the means of all his activity. That is the only one which remains constant and unchanging at all times and in all states of his experience. That is why that Self is permanent as far as he is concerned. That is the “Sadvastu” or the Real and True Entity. That is why the Vedas say –

Through such sacred utterances, it is said that the self-stuff (Atma Vastu) is the biggest of all. Following this, Apastamba Maharshi, the Smriti maker has said – And has reached the conclusion that there is no greater gain than self-knowledge.

Thus, the Self, Self-Realization, the opportunity for this Realization of the Self – this is the ultimate Good which is the epistemological measure determining the hierarchy of values regarding all things in the world, all glorious things, all our desires and our experiences of all objects and substances – this is the means, the determining Dharma or Right conduct that is the seed of culture.

The Arrangement of the Goal of Life

What has resulted following this principle is the arrangement of the four – fold values of life or “Purusharthas”. “Purushartha” means man’s desire or goal. That which he considers valuable or desirable is “Artha”. In English it is called “Value”. Whatever the endeavour or employment of man, it comes under the preview of one of the four object, types of uses, namely Dharma, Artha, Kama and Moksha. (1) The works that are undertaken to achieve progress in this world or to attain a good life hereafter and the means thereof is “Dharma”. All the family and social duties are “Dharma”. (2) The acquisition of the means of obtaining it, be it money or produce etc. is “Artha”. (3) The various kinds of longings and desires are “Karma”. (4) Transcending all desired and being pure, wanting liberation and realizing the ultimate with no other thought is “Moksha”. These four endeavours in life – when they are in the control of the memory of the inner Being – nothing is eschewed; all things become acceptable. But they must be in a state of equilibrium. In the Mahabharata it is said:

He who sees to it that there is no mutual conflict between Dharma and Artha, between Dharma and Kama, between Kama and Artha and enjoys all these aspects, Dharma, Artha and Kama attains the greatest happiness.

(Every day, first Dharma, second Artha (money) and finally bhoga are to be achieved. This is the injunction of the Sastra)[*].

Here the description of Moksha is not clear. It is implied. Here Moksha is an occurrence beyond the world. Moksha is an accomplished fact for him who has achieved the three worldly ideals. When all the mud, dust and debris covering the treasure that has been buried in a hole in the ground is cleared the precious jewels shine forth on their own. There is no special effort required to make them shine. Thus through the three – fold ideal with its contact with the world is washed clean away in life. Then the self - effulgent inner Being reveals itself by itself.

The Self is that which remains like an emperor imbedded in all objects that appear to man both directly and indirectly. The highest achievement and culmination for man is the full revelation of that, this journey of life in order to get that vision is what makes his life purposeful. The two sides or borders of the road that he takes are “Pravritti Dharma” and “Nivritti Dharma”. Pravritti Dharma consists of training in areas like the family, religion, employment and in centres of the country and geographical area of his living. Nivritti Dharma consists of external and internal cleanliness, charity, control of senses, worship, meditation, sacrifice, disinterestedness, etc.

Many manifestations of the Nivritti Dharma may not be understood by people who skim only the surface. They say “What is the use of fasting?” They ask “Why shout Bhajans? Is God deaf ?” They have not known the turmoils of life. They do not know how to bring courage and strength to life. The secrets of spiritual cultivation, as far as several people of today are concerned – many educated among them – have become like a secret that is whispered for a deaf man. What is uttered is one thing – what is heard is quite another. Just as the senses of vision, senses of hearing, the senses of smell are different, similarly the inner sense organ which can cognize the metaphysical is different. That is the inner vision. That is the inner instruction. For those for whom it is not tuned and trained, the philosophical truths are like a musical instrument played in front of a deaf man or a dance performed in front of a blind man.

Those who believe that there is the Self – there is an individual self and there is an ultimate Self, they weigh everything in the scale of the good of the Supreme Self and determine value. An object is valued according to the proportion of “Sat” (Truth content) in it. Thus the main measure in the calculation of culture is the remembrance of the ultimate Essence – the absolute Self, God, the Lord of the universe.

That human culture which is of this kind deserves the name “Daivi Sampath”. The Bhagavadgita describes its characteristics this way:

“Sattvasamshuddhi” means being without taint in one’s mature, “Shaucha” means purity, “Shuchi” means transparently clean. The Shine which results from cleanliness is given great importance by the Veda; thus:

We must keep not only our bodies clean but our minds also. As Purandhara Dasa has said “You must clean your minds”.

Because for the unwashed mind, the nuances of the atmospheric differences do not immediately become clear. Just as for a clean hand, the fine and rough things become clear on touch, for the purified mind the surrounding fineness and sophistication becomes clear at one. It is this sensitiveness that we should attain and maintain morally. Just as the string of a Veena vibrates for the wind, pure heart vibrates in response to the surrounding atmosphere. The level and extent of that sensitiveness determines the extent and sensitiveness of the individual moral fibre. Just as the singer the flute, the runner the feet, the goldsmith the finger and the painter his eye, the cultured man protects his conscience from being polluted by the atmosphere. He in whose inner conscience the do’s and don’ts flash forth instantly, his outer behaviour gets beautified automatically.

Hindu Culture

The two quintessential aspects of Hindu Culture may be said to be supreme importance given to inner life and the philosophical attitude in the carrying on of the worldly affairs. We fix the value for all objects and relationships from the point of view of inner vision. After cogitating thus, arranging and organizing our priorities without doing damage to the higher goal from the lesser, by reconciling and unifying the four-fold ideal – living this way is Dharma. That is the inner core of the Veda and Vedanta system. The self-stuff is indestructible – eternal. It has to enjoy and suffer as results of its own previous actions. This individual selfhood and its history of past actions is beginningless. Similarly is this world beginningless. The ups and down of the individual self are according to the meritorious and mean actions. It earns its existence in other worlds. The individual self gets its relationship with the world according to its own earlier credits and debits. Though such is the binding in the individual body’s breath, new air is mixing with the old air every minute, to the extent of man trying to free himself from old bondage, new breath, new independent respiration will always be arising. He can attain the grace of God through devotion, helping others, meditation and performance of tapas. The individual self by curtailing desire and avarice by practicing disinterestedness and egolessness, attaining self-control and the discriminating knowledge of the difference between the Self and the non-self, through the practice of the Right conduct, that jiva or individual self can rise above the shackles of the cage. Then it gets the knowledge of the Pure Self – the vision of the complete Self. Then gradually the direct vision of God – the plenary experience of Brahman. That is “Moksha” or Liberation from worldly bondage. That is Hindu culture which is based on this trend of thought being followed for thousands of years by our people.

Though the word culture is new to us, its meaning is not new. That beauty of social behaviour which has been known to us since old times by the words mildness, gentlemanliness, kindness, smoothness, submissiveness, respect, generosity, etc. – these are the stuff of culture. Saltness, sourness, pungency and jaggery, where they are by themselves separately, they look mutually contradictory. When they are mixed in a certain proportion in saaru (Rasam) in an agreeable manner, that potion assures distinctively different taste different from each ingredient and extremely taste palatable. Sandalwood, civet (the sweet aroma emanating from a certain type of eat), a type of camphor, saffron, though they are not opposed to each other smell differently. But when they are mixed in a certain proportion, a special aroma seemingly a fifth one arises. Similarly education, politeness, cleverness, courage, compassion, humour, bravery, adventure, dignity, these qualities when they are combined, as a result, a tenth, a beauty of conduct makes its appearance. Where that is present, there will be no room for fear and no opportunity for selfishness. It engenders mutual trust and confidence among people. But it doesn’t obliterate respect. All in all, it creates an atmosphere of friendship and peace. Such is the benefit of culture. Then as a result of maturity, the self is a latent glow emanating always. It is a symphony of feeling.

Let us take an example. All our Sruthis and Smritis say that truth is the ultimate Dharma don’t they? Truth means actuality. Speaking and acting according to what has appeared to us exactly as it has is truth. If this is said the essence of truth seems very simple. It is neither so simple nor easy.

The great Manu has decreed truthful behaviour thus – “Truth must be told: that which is pleasant must be told.

Truth which is unpleasant must not be told. That which is pleasant but untruthful must not be told either”.

Let us compare this advice with another and discuss it.

“It is said that what is retained unsaid is superior to what is actually said. When it is necessary to speak out, only truth must be said”.

Silence is better than speech. This is the first principle. If something has to be spoken only truth must be said. This is the second principle. That a pleasant thing must be spoken is the third. That what is spoken must be according to and in keeping with Dharma is the fourth aphorism.

What does it all amount to? (1) As far as possible, silence should be maintained; speech must be minimized. When Dharma doesn’t demand talk, speech must be avoided. (2) When speech becomes necessary it must be spoken according to the approval by truth, it must give up a harsh demeanor and wear the gasp of pleasant exterior and must act to subserve the interest of Dharma and bring benefit to all parties.

There is a method in truth speaking. In many human situations, truth may seem to trust. There is the famous proverb “One who speaks the harsh truth antagonizes the world”. Still, it is the uniqueness of culture to get rid of the harshness and reveal the truth in its mild form. The method and manner of speaking the truth has to be determined by a sense of discrimination and the understanding of the context. Thus speaking the truth is not a mechanical act, it is a well thought about act.

That is the opinion of Sage Manu.

What is true and what is pleasant are not the same thing. Often, not only are they different, but are mutually opposed to each other. In such circumstances removing the unpleasantness while speaking the truth and removing the untruth while speaking what is pleasant is approved by Dharma. After saying this, in providing a bodily sheath to truth in words, a critical appraisal strategy become necessary.

Pure truth is like ginger. The doctor doesn’t make a patient eat it just as it is. He “cures” it – i.e. he mixes it with other edible things thus refining it, reduces its pungency and gives it to the patient.

Such a thing is the work of culture.

The Finesse in the Depiction of Truth

Bharata’s Experience

An example of this is provided by the poet Bhasa in his play “Pratima Nataka”. The situation there pertains to the episode of Bharata being informed of his father’s death. After Sri Rama leaves for the forest, when his father Dasaratha passes away, Bharata was at Rajagriha, his maternal uncle’s capital. The Guru, Sage Vasistha sends a messenger to bring him. As soon as he sees the messenger Bharata enquires after the health of his father. The messenger without telling him that Dasaratha is dead, only informs him that he sank to the ground overcome by a heart attack. They start from there and come to Ayodhya. Even then the messenger did not give out the whole truth. His mind hesitates to speak out directly the harsh truth. He thinks:

Precisely at that time a messenger comes and delivers the message sent by the Preceptor that it was still the duration of the star Krittika and that after a little while when the star Rohini would be reigning, Bharata could then enter the city. Accordingly, with the intention of relaxing in the garden for some time, while searching for a suitable place to do so, he beholds a temple. Bharata enters the temple and sees the row of statues adorned by sandle paste and flowers. When he is thinking of prostrating to them, the Priest enters and says that it is not proper for him to do so.

Bharata : “These must be Kshatriyas. What are their names?” Priest : “They are Ikshvakus”.

Bharata : “Ikshvakus? Then they are the kings of Ayodhya. By my good fortune I have now the opportunity to meet them. Who is this other one?”

Priest : “He is Dilipa, one who lighted up the world with his Righteousness.”

Bharata : “My salutations to him, who was immersed in Dharma. Who is this?”

Priest : “Raghu Maharaja – a beneficiary of the blessings of thousands of Brahmins.”

Bharata : “How powerful is Death. It transgressed even the blessings of Brahmin. My pranams to Raghu.

Who is this other?”

Priest : “Kind Aja who was without blemish through the performance of many sacrifices. When his beloved died, he gave up his kingship.”

Bharata : “My obeisances to him who had the praiseworthy contrition.

When Bharata was saying this, his gaze travels to the fourth statue – that of Dasaratha. Then, since he hadn’t heard the names of the earlier three with care, he asks the priest to repeat their names. He repeats once again. “This is Dilipa, this is Raghu, this is Aja”. Bharata salutes them separately, severally and asks for the names again. The priest does so. When for the last time the name of Aja is mentioned Bharata tries to remember his relationship with his father by asking “Is he not the father of Maharaja Dasaratha?” He asks the priest “Are the statues of living people kept here?” The priest answers “No, only the statues of the dead are kept here”. And explains –

Bharata swoons on hearing this. Then he recovers. The story proceeds.

When Bharata remembers the stories about his ancestors through their statues, the latent devotion towards them hiding in the depths of his memory becomes patent. He pays his homage to each one of them standing in front of the likeness of each ancestor in a chronological order. Thus step by step, by the time he comes to Dasaratha, his mind would have reached a certain philosophical disinterestedness. By contemplating on great people his soul would have reached having beholden a hair-raising ennobling sight. The transient, small-minded emotions would have evaporated and only a long-lasting picture of greatness would be visible before him. Another memory of nobility would have mingled with it. For Raghu who was pure by his very birth, for Dilipa who was universally admired, for legendary Aja, for none of these did Death make a concession. The glory of this world does end one day, no matter how great the man. The paths of glory lead but to the grave. Bharata’s mind would be filled with this philosophy of time. Thus the news of Dasaratha’s death reaches his mind when it has been reminded of the memory of his ancestors, the powerful influence of time and the gravity of the human condition. It was the “culture” of sage Vasistha that he had arranged the timing of the entrance to the city preparing it for receiving the sad news. Not that Bharata’s sorrow was alloyed by this preparation: but its impact must have been softened by this. Supposing without either through the device of the statues or by some other means, Bharata had been bluntly told “Bharata, your father is dead”. What might be the damage for his mind! If we can guess by our common knowledge the mental state of Bharata by a sudden rough announcement of the devastating news without Guru Vasistha’s timely plan, we can surely say that the device considerably arranged the bluntness of the blow.

Culture is the mode and the method which takes away the string and cruelty from a tragic situation, the pangs of the news of death and the sharpness of the words and ways of rough human behaviour. That which takes away the roughness from a rough situation, the pungency from a pungent circumstance that is culture.

Sage Vasistha did not suppress the truth as it was unpleasant. But he did not allow the unpleasantness in its cruel aspect. This is the import of the above statement quoted from Manu.

The Example of Macbeth

Let us look at another example. This is from Shakespeare. In the play Macbeth, Lady Macbeth would have lost her mind. Macbeth summons the doctor and asks him to treat her. She is the king’s dear one – a partner in his actions. So it is that her state of mind grieves him. We must observe in what words he informs the doctor this news which has plunged his own mind in a frightening state. Does he say that his wife has gone mad? No. “Madness”. “Distemper”, “Mind’s disease” are harsh words. For the speaker of these words, his own mind suffers while speaking. Macbeth who was loving to speak such words about his beloved is not approved by his mind. So he expresses his mental stress in smooth and soft words.

Can’st then not minister to a mind diseas’d;
Pluck from the memory a rooted sorrow;
Raze out the written troubles of brain;
And with same sweet oblivious antidote,
Cleanse the stuff ’d bosom of that perilous stuff,
Which weighs upon the heart?

Macbeth V, iv, 40-45.

Tr uth has not been hidden here. Only its simple unpleasantness has been somewhat veiled.

The manner of speech that has been followed by Macbeth here is called ‘Tact’ in English. We can say it is “dexterity in speech”. The special characteristic of this kind of communication skill consists of using a method of not displeasing others, but without sacrificing the interests of truth or acting with previously planned self-control. Untruth and injustice need not be present in the smooth concourse. But if crudity and roughness are contained in the truth, “tact” removes only the lack of sophistication. John Morley has said that tact is something that is the ultimate benefit that is bestowed on us by the study of literature. The fruit of the contemplation of good literature and philosophy is that it gives this smooth behaviour; and the resultant controlled use of words, the ability to bifurcate roughness from speech and smoothen it.

Another example. In Hamlet, another famous play of Shakespeare when the Queen wants to have a private conversation with the King, what does she say in order to send away the retinue?

Bestow this place on us a little while.[*]

Hamlet, IV, i, 4

Sri Bhudeva Mukhyapadhaya had strated a fund which he named

‘Vishwanatha Fund’ in the memory of Viswanatha Tarkabhushana. He had donated for this fund his entire property of One lakh and six thousand rupees. Out of this fund an annual remuneration of fifty rupees would be paid unasked at their own home by money order to learned and pious Brahmins of India.

The same people who publish the “Education Gazette” had prepared this first year’s report. It contained a sentence which said “The names of those scholars who have been given this year’s “Viswanatha” Award. Sri Bhudeva, when he read this sentence expressed displeasure and instructed that the sentence should be re- framed thus. “The names of scholars who have kindly agreed to accept the “Viswanatha Award” – “Jeevottama Magazine, Kumta, dated 25.02.1966”.

Truth and Dharma

When we say that milk is the best food, what we have in our mind as the intention is the suitability of milk as food. Similarly what makes truth invaluable is its Dharmic possibility; for Dharma truth is essential. Therefore, truth is a duty for us. Then is there truth which is not essential to Dharma?. Yes, there is. For the people who have a vast experience in different fields, for those who have observed with a keen and critical eye, truth is not only irrelevant but can sometimes be inimical. The truth at the level of word may be counter productive in action. There is an illustration in Mahabharata. Let us look at it.

The Mistake of Arjuna

The battle is taking place at Kurukshetra. Arjuna will have come to the battle field after swearing to Dharmaraya that he would finish off Karna. Believing it, Dharmaraya, out of curiosity would be leading the array in another part of the field. A fierce war takes place that day. In one area, the flood of arrows raining fiercely will be attacking Yudhishtira released by Karna, inspired by Shalya. He recedes to his camp unable to bear the pain of wounds. In another part of the field pressuring the enemy, Arjuna, not finding Yudhishtira anywhere, on hearing the news and perturbed, comes to the camp to see his elder brother. Yudhishtira’s mind is full of anxiety and expectation to hear the news of Karna’s death. In that charged situation “he will be under the impression that Arjuna has brought the desired news. But Arjuna tells him how he was belabored by Aswatthama and while escaping came to hear the tragic news about his brother and he has come to make enquiries. Yudhishtira mistakes this as an un- providing and gets augmented in his anger which was already burning in him. In that fury and excitement he condemns him in all sorts of ways and curses him. “Throw away your Gandiva (Arjuna’s powerful bow). Let there be contempt for your called valour. May your flag and your chariot be ruined.” Arjuna’s reply is equally full of lightning and thunder. Between the two sits Krishna as a silent witness. Then Arjuna hissing like a black cobra turns to Krishna and says “Govinda, you know my oath. I will cut off the head of anyone who asks me to throw away my Gandiva”. Saying so, he pulls his sword from his sheath. Then all his attention is concentrated on the truth of oath he had taken. Parthasarathy (Krishna) who was silent till then, speaks about the secret of Dharma. He addresses Arjuna – “My dear man, what do you know about the true nature of truth? Have your served old men? Have you understood the nuances of Dharma? Have you known about the circumstances when truth can become falsehood and falsehood can become truth?”

(It is right that truth has to be spoken. Falsehood may have to be spoken too. There are circumstances when falsehood can bring good like truth and truth can bring misfortune like lies).

In a certain circumstance what is to be spoken, whether truth or falsehood is answered only by the discriminatory process of Dharma. What makes for Dharma has to be spoken. Dharma means that which brings about the good of the world. Krishna says:

(That speech or conduct which results in bringing about good to the world is Dharma. That means that truth, whether it is to be spoken or not spoken has to be determined by taking into account the resultant fruit).

(That is truth which is the means of engendering the maximum good to all living beings).

(Truthful speech is certainly beneficial. But it is difficult to know what exactly it is).

In order to bring about harmony in marriage which is the main support of society, in order to protect the self-respect of men and women, in order to prevent the slaughter of animals, to stop the erosion and ebbing away of the stuff of life, and in order to protect the rule of righteousness in an all-indusive manner – in these five noble causes, the falsehood that is uttered is not a sin.

Which devoted wife does not exaggerate the good qualities of her husband while talking to others about him and does not hide his defects? Is this not more praiseworthy than weighing the good and bad in the balance of truth? A cultured man cannot say that her “lies” are sinful. He admires it smilingly.

The Story of Kaushika

A word may be truthful in a certain external sense. The action in its result may be the cause of adharma or wrong doing. Sri Krishna himself tells Arjuna a story.

“In a forest, it seems there was a sage by name Kaushika performing penance. He was a teller of truth. On a certain day, some travellers went running. After a little while some thieves came to him and asked “Did some people go this way? Speak the truth”. Since Kaushika was a teller of truth, he replied “Yes. Some people went that way in the director of the yonder bushes and the grove”. Those robbers were satisfied by his words. They went in the direction pointed out by Kaushika, caught hold of the innocent pilgrims and carried out their wishes. What was the result of the truth spoken by Kaushika? Arjuna, the truth of the oath taken by you about Gandiva is of the same sort!”

What Krishna said was a subtle nuance of Dharma. What makes this subtlety clear is the way of discrimination. The behaviour resulting from it is character. A man who has made such a behaviour, his very character and inner nature is a cultured man.

It is said that in a bunch of hundred bananas, at the tip of one of them there will be a drop of nectar. In a huge heap of corn flour, a grain of life-supporting element, the size of a mustard seed will be hiding. Similarly in a cart-load of do’s and don’ts, the subtlety of right conduct of the size of a speck will be present somewhere, enveloping the whole thing. This atom of righteousness is the very life of the ultimate well-being. The very essence of Dharmartha that makes the existence of dharma dwells in this ray of this atom. That is dharma which is contained in the character and conduct permeating that beneficial ray. The external behaviour is only the body of Dharma, the body is essential; but mere external body is not enough. There must be the inner Essence. The knowledge of that inner “elon vital” is the loadstone or magnet that is gained by culture.

The Synthesis of Various Virtues

When in the case of the practice of truth which is the very essence of Dharma, so many qualifications and restrictions are required, many words are not necessary to express how careful we must be in the case of other good qualities. Whatever the virtue which we consider supreme, if it is not subject to a certain delicate rules and regulations, it cannot bring about the best results. Moderation is the method of the fulfillment of good. It is only one half of moral science that those opposed to good qualities are bad qualities; the remaining half consists of the possibilities of human situations where good qualities are opposed to other good qualities. For example, let us look at the two lists of good.

(1) | (2)
Nobility | Simplicity
Maturity | Humility
Courage | Circumspection
Confidence in one’s belief | Curiosity about the opposition
A brave resolve | Preparation for friendliness
Living alone | Synthesis of everyone’s welfare
Independence | Respect for others
Commitment to one’s own | Forgiveness of other’s defeats
conviction

In the above list the qualities of both categories seem complementary But for a critical eye the two aspects of horizontal words in each line seem to be contradictory. It is not usual to find great condition and simple behaviour of an ordinary man in the same man. Similarly it is not common to see dedication to one’s one creed and the tolerance of another belief in the same individual. One does not ordinarily find an independent mind and heeding the other’s point of view together Thus a commendable quality existing separately by itself, if it has to integrate with an equally good quality which is different, assumes a defiant attitude. The quality of devotion and right conduct towards the mother is the same as that concerned with wife. But when the mother and wife are at loggerheads the unified devotion to mother and the love of the wife which should be unison go in separate ways and break away. In such circumstances acting according to propriety and integrating them, this tact is that of culture.

It is possible that everyone agrees that love of one’s own country and one’s own people are commendable qualities. Thinking of the welfare of entire world and love all humanity are good qualities, in the same way. But what is near is making a lot of noise, remembering what is dear and just in a distant thing is possible only for a cultured mind.

For human life to become fully happy, the development of one or two qualities is not enough. Hundreds of good qualities must mingle together in mutual friendliness.

Similarly, the interests and goals of our lives are in hundreds. Our aims should be projecting themselves in myriad directions. Our loves will be tied up in different places. We won’t be able to discard any one of them. That is the reason why we cannot allow disproportionate growth to any one of them. One of them becomes the cause for limiting another. The responsibility of culture is creating the synthesis of disparate through the discriminatory sense of its limits – the synthesis of commingling in various loves.

Culture makes all areas of life into one unit and looks at the whole thing as impartite. The cultured man makes his own good a part of the good of the town – that of the town as a portion of the country, the history of the country as a portion of the human world, the earth as a segment of the Universe. He will have practiced to think that way. He compares and relates the air he breathes to the clouds in the sky. He thinks of the sparkle in the eyes of the child playing in front of him as akin to the stars. This kind of expansive feeling is the boon we can obtain from culture.

The Sources of Culture

The sources of culture are not, one, two, ten, a hundred. These can be divided into six units.

The Divine Religious injunctions: The imbedded aspects in this are – the extra sensory metaphysical speculations of Shruti (scriptures), Smrithi (sacred recollected utterances and Puranas – the Myths and Legends), the different types of conclusions drawn from them, the modes of worship, meditation and practices, the methods of ritual do’s and dont’s leading to the search of soul and codes of conduct and behaviour.
Literature and other Fine Arts: In this are included the imaginary worlds which are emotion oriented found in poetry and drama and aesthetic happenings like music, sculpture, dance and allied subjects.
Science: In this are placed Physics, Biology and Philosophical enquiry into the origin of creation and education of man regarding Politics and Economics.
The National and the International History and the account of great men.
The influence of one’s own Society: The atmosphere of individual’s religion, caste and group, the nature of his own region; the background of his profession and that of his friends and associates – these various intertwining aspects do continue to influence the character and behaviour of each and every individual. The individual culture cannot escape completely the influence of societal culture. After all, the culture of a society is the sum – total of the effects of mutual individual reactions. The more the sophistication of society, the better the individual culture.
Man’s internal search and control: Through this the impurities which were natural to him disappear and they become simple and touching expressions. Thus his value system becomes delicate and discriminatory. His priorities become refined.

The first five result in the sixth. The inner sanctity of life is the fruit of refinement of the mind on one side and the refinement of the heart on the other. The perfume that emanates from such a mature life is culture.

Culture is not a simple thing, it is a Compound. It does not have a single limb, but many. It is the net result of the resolution of many kind of conflict and arrangements. It is like a bouquet of many kinds of flowers; it is like a perfume compounded of ingredients like civet, saffron and such other sweet-smelling ingredients; its interest is because of the manifold components. The beauty exists not because of the similarity in the quality or appearance of objects but in friendship and co-operation of the dissimilarities in other qualities and looks. No single quality or appearance of objects but in friendship and co-operation of the dissimilarities in other qualities and looks. No single quality or appearance when it is by itself is a cause of beauty. The facts are necessary when it is by itself is a cause of beauty. The facts are necessary to make for geniusness of beauty or shapely appearance complete. (1) There should be many forms and qualities, and each shape and characteristic must by itself stand by itself in unison. (2) Each separate thing must melt into the neighbouring forms and virtues and must refine itself – its individuality – to augment the beauty of the totality. Thus each substance must have both the qualities of its own flowering forth and the preparedness of mingling.

One can see both these things in the parts of a healthy man. The arm will be powerful; but it doesn’t swallow up the nourishment due to the legs. The eyes will be sharp but it doesn’t deafen the ears. There will be the efficiency of each organ as well as mutual friendly feeling. It is because of this there is concordance; This is mutual agreement, this is propriety.

Individual and Society

Is Culture born of the individual or the society? Is it embedded in the individual or the society? This question arises from the assumed feeling that the individual and society cannot exist independently of each other. For those who are experienced in worldly affairs, it is clear that this distinction has no foundation. Home, birth, profession and the political system – all these influence the individual every moment. The individual also exercises his influence on them unceasingly. Thus culture will keep on getting shaped by the mutual influence of the individual and society.

Aren’t there divisions like birth, caste, race, region in the human world? In the beginning these divisions happened because of natural causes. The geographical and atmospheric factors would have shaped the bodies and minds of people. Afterwords their religions affiliations give a turn to their mental attitudes. Their economic situation and employment circumstances shape their character and behaviour. Similarly the history of their country determines their virtues and vices. Thus one account of innate comes various practices, behavioural patterns will have taken root in different societies. The differences in birth, race, category and caste have happened because of these differences in practices and traditions. These groups are not artificially generated by an individual or a group. Nobody has broken something which was a whole. By birth itself, the sibling had ten branches. And neither is it a matter for a lacuna. The beauty of the bush is because of the ten differences of the ten. What is desirable to us is not the destruction of the variety. The melting of variety – not the monotony of a sameness but a synthesis. When the “saaru” (hot porridge) is tasty, the salt and the sour don’t have to become proper; pepper also is incapable of becoming sour and salty; there is neither the necessity for all the three to become jaggery. Each substance must retain its own taste, but it must mix properly. This proper mixture is the taste of “saaru”. Those who know this truth, when they hear slogans like “class-less society”, “caste-less society” cannot but think that they are blind outcries.

There is no caste or class-wall separating Russia and America. Eating together and inter-marrying is not forbidden there. But why can’t the two of them become a single nation? Or even become friends? Why can’t France and England unite? Why can’t the entire Europe become a single society? It can’t happen; the reason is that the root-cause for the diverse societies, groups and parties are certain natural causes and innate propensities. It is not possible to change those today. When the world (globe) becomes flat like a mat instead of being round, when the sun starts shedding his heat and light with the same intensity simultaneously on India and Siberia, when the wind and the clouds move with the same speed, cold moisture and speed every minute of the day and night, then and only is there a possibility of the human differences dissolving into a single shape and all differences being exterminated. Until that time the differences between human groups exist inevitably in one way or the other.

Cannot the scientists make all creation into the same single unit by making changes in the composition of the earth and the very nature of the sky and ether? Perhaps they can. If they do that, then what is the difference between that and “Pralaya” – the ultimate dissolution? Isn’t dissolution also a single state? – everything burnt down into ashes! Everything melting into water!

Then there are not many; everything is impartite; everything is a single unit; but everything lifeless; everything empty, everything a vacuum.

Life means myriad activities dancing about without the monotony of a single lifeless state. No living being, no animal is completely like another; no form of birth is fully like another. In each individual there is a special quality. This quintessential uniqueness is individuality. The attraction of the world of living entities is because of this inscape of in stress.

The myriadness and variety is the work of Nature.

The uniqueness of the Knower, the wise person is to see the oneness of Reality behind the existing superficial myriadness.

Freedom for Culture

Culture is something that takes place as a result of contact with the world; it is a requisite for worldly life; still its primary entity is the individual.

Culture can be compared to a large wood or garden. In a garden there will be dozens of varieties of trees, plants, creepers and hundreds of bushes. In this vast society of vegetation the wind of one blows on the other; the shade of one falls on the other; the roots of one touch those of the other; thus the development of one touches and transforms the other considerably. Inspite of all these neighbourly contacts the life of each plant will be its own with its difference. Grass does not become jasmine, the neem does not become mango; the tamarind does not become jackfruit. The height or the shortness of a plant, the shape and width of its branches, the thickness or the thinness of it – are determined by its surroundings and situations. But the smell of its flowers, the taste of its fruits do not change into anything unrecognizable by its neighbourhood. That smell, that taste is the essence of that individual. The collective good qualities constitute the beauty of that garden. The same thing applies to human culture. It is the extent to which the individual culture improves to that extent does the development of the total society of all people happens.

The same manner in which a plant gives its own flowers and fruits, it cannot forego its own natural inner need in what it takes. The tree selects and absorbs the things it needs from the earth, the water, the wind and the sun; it lets out what it doesn’t need; all that is needed by the sugarcane is not needed by the gram; what is sufficient for the Bengal gram is insufficient for the coconut. Thus the need of each individual entity has its own preference, chosen by its own inner propensity.

A good gardener knows these individual requirements. He will have known about the price and value of each tree and plant in the beginning itself. Then after considering the differences, he distributes his interests. If a plant that is worth ten points is likely to get affected by one who is worth only five, then he transfers the less profitable one to some other place. Thus knowing the differences between the lesser and the greater, he increases the opportunities for the more profitable ones. He makes room when there is congestion. He pulls out the weeds and clears the ground. He digs a repository of water around the plant. All these are acts of promoting individual merits. A garden is good because of ten good plants; not by a hundred weeds.

For the betterment of the value of a tribe or a society, the individuals must have unlimited opportunity to develop their own native skills. The real freedom is only this wide-ranging opportunities to express himself – his own self. If a plant has to put forth flowers, it must have the freedom to turn its head in the direction of the Sun, its space to spread its branches under the shade and to absorb the life-living essences of the earth. This kind of freedom that is given finds its justification in the flowers and fruits it puts forth. The story of man’s development of culture is also like that.

The Advantage for Situation

There are certain necessary conditions and advantages for the development of culture. First of all a man must have peace of mind. That peace comes about from well-organized external circumstances. He must have the confidence that his food, his house, his profession and his income – these things which he has organized for himself must continue as he has planned their continuance must be assured. He must never have a suspicion in his mind that they might, sometime, somehow, may be jeopardized. The guarantee regarding his life is the source of his peace of mind.

Then he should not have the fear that others might interfere in his endeavours. The works that he has undertaken according to his inspiration and mind will continue – he himself is the dictator of his desires – this assurance he must possess.

Thirdly, he must have leisure. If there is an abundance of worry regarding the income for his livelihood or the anxieties of diminishing his enthusiasm, the equanimity of the mind will be spoilt. A mind without rest is like a house without a front yard and a backyard; it is like a paddy field where sowing starts immediately after the crop has been reaped. We must not forget that for development leisure and rest are a necessary preparation.

Fourthly, in his surrounding society there must be encouragement for the search for excellence. No matter how brilliant a man, however great he may be as a scholar; he cannot rise much above his situation and atmosphere; no man can escape the influence of his surroundings. To the extent to which a people’s mind is filled with idealism in a society, to that extent will the individual’s encouragement for culture exists. When there is no inspiration for progress in the atmosphere, the effort for cultivation of culture is like an effort to find water by digging a well in a desert. Thus, peace, safety, leisure, desire for progress – these are the prerequisites for the development of culture.

In our country, at the time of epics and the great works of art were born, the society possessed those characteristics. Kalidasa, Jayadeva, Jakkana, Sayama, Purandara, Tyagaraja – These did not seem to have faced the tyranny of the kings or conquests and onslaughts by enemies or perversity in their social order in the cultivation of their inner self. The attitude of the ancestors was – let the king mind his own business; let the wars be fought by themselves if they have to be fought; let our safety and the household and societal order be under our careful supervision. Now until about fifty years ago, in our country, except some very small villages, in every town there would be at least one or two scholars and artists. The mad slogan – mongering of the positions, crying house for revolution, the laws regarding the distribution of property rights, the amendments of laws and their vicissitudes, the noisy demonstrations due to caste envy – these things hadn’t come in the way and hindered the literary giants and musicians. They would be satisfied being content with the produce obtained from their lands, with the income obtained by following their own family trade and profession and devoting the rest of their time in the study of literature, listening to the praise of the Lord in the Puranas and Harikathas etc. The result of this was reflected in their social conduct and behaviour, their politeness and softness of their speech and mild manner. This is the essence of culture.

Today’s is a world of competition. No matter where you look – in whatever aspect of life. A thousand people will be fighting each other to secure a place and position in a rat race to be first in the line – for education, for jobs, for trade, for political position and for anything and everything. Competition, confrontation and adventure everywhere. Even a scholar or a teacher has to advertise in a proper place in a newspaper. The aspirants must fill in applications. He must wait at the doors of selection committee members after finding out their convenient time and blow his own trumpet. Even there, there is no entry without publicity. Unless a person struggles and fights with the next man and topples him either by trickery or strength, nobody can earn a living. This egotistic hand to hand and head to head combat is increasing in our country as our contact with other countries is increasing, where the worlds come together, there is a vanity fare. The denser the participation, the greater is the competition. In this exhibitionism each person has to attract attention to himself. That necessitates his patting himself on his back and blowing his own trumpet loud and clear. If he waits for others to recognize him, it may be too late. A man who does not provide himself to the skies does not get to eat.

But the character of a cultured man is different.

[When four people gather together to discuss who is virtuous and when they decide to count and start by folding the little finger, that person’s name which does not automatically result in folding the finger enthusiastically, how can the mother who has given birth to him be called a good mother (Sutani) and bringing forth such a man does not make her any better than a barren woman. If she is considered a “mother then who is a barren woman”]

Which means that when a son is voluntarily admired as a virtuous gentleman, then the motherhood of that mother invites respect. One who cannot win respect that way and he himself has to push forward and advertise himself “I am not inferior to anyone” and one who has to invite himself to a dinner when nobody invites him (a popular proverb in Kannada), the woman who has given birth to such a man, her motherhood is not in any way superior to barrenness – such is the opinion of our ancestors.

In our political establishment in electing a candidate, a man who gets six votes is considered better than the man who gets only five. Those who derive satisfaction by such recommendations, it would not be out of place for them to read and contemplate on the meaning of the above stanza.

Culture and Government

Ours is an age of heavenly dreams. The intention of our political policy is the upliftment of everybody. Our goal is universal equality. Our approach to religion is mutually restritive. In the name of general good, everybody must be pressurizing everybody. No one should leave anyone alone. No one should have the opportunity to be left in peace. The people should not leave the government alone; the government should not leave anybody alone. What should be eaten; how much; what should be worn; how much, what should be sung; what should be heard; what should be learnt, what should be spoken – all these are prescribed by either the government or by the society in our new dispensation. Now the individual is only the footwear of a monster. The likes and dislikes of society are not a result of culture, the taste and desires are only the imitations of other people; whatever makes our tongues water, it is good for us. Whatever glitters is gold; whatever is smooth and polished is a precious stone. Perpetual motion without looking before and after is our “Karmayoga”. Sensory perceptions is our main proof. Feeding the senses and pampering them is our supreme happiness. Such things are today our notion of progress. When this is the ideal of our national leaders, where is the room for individual freedom? Where is the value for culture?

For true culture the progress of the inner soul is of greater importance than that of physical and empirical progress. What it desires is not pampering and pondering to the senses, but our inner self-searching. Its main target is not society but the individual. Its way is not the confusion of the higher and the lower. But the discrimination is between the two. Culture does not accept blindly the new-tangled notions of equality and non- difference without examining them. Only so far as the rules and regulations of society are supportive of an co-operative to the individual’s character-building and its purification, they are beneficial. To the extent where individual life does not endanger the good of the society, there the individual’s own freedom should not be tampered within the name of society or nation. The loss affecting the individuality of the individual is a loss pertaining to the nation. This is the lesson of culture.

We have no opportunity to know the extent of the inner workings of the ways of culture that have been understood by our national leaders who are crying hoarse about culture. They are showing their love of various religions and various persuasions. At one time they say they want private initiative. At another time they say they want nationalization. At one time publicity for social equality; at another time encouragement for personal power. At one time a secular government, at another time a religion – oriented government; today a progressive world- view, the next day devotion to old traditional ways; this minute machine and industrial oriented dedication, the next minute support for rural and village handicrafts. Thus our bosses one dancing this way and that. Are these pre-occupations which are mutually destructive – should these be synthesized into culture, or culture itself is paramount?

The day on which culture becomes important enough for us when all dual perceptions are merged in its light, there may be a complementary understanding, but it doesn’t look as though the stars are favorable for culture at the present juncture.

Culture is a great achievement. Government and politicians might keep invoking its name while forgetting its meaning and spend time taking shelter in its shade. We can, however, individually and severally earn and achieve culture at least to some extent. Let us take it as far as we can through personal effort and dedication.

Questions for Indian Culture

Indian culture is a composite thing. It has come into existence as a result of many types of emotional states, various types of situational inspirations and their integration. One can say that its main root are the Vedas. In that mountain range there are many peaks. The verbal totality of the Vedas as we know it today has taken thousands of years to take this shape. Beginning with the worship of nature deities like Indra, Varuna, Agni and Vayu and spreading through sacrifices like Agnisthoma, Vajapeya and Rajasuya and finding fruition and culmination in the philosophical concept of the oneness and non-duality of Jeeva and Brahman, containing within itself the vision of hundreds of sages and saints, developed through various thoughts and arguments in dozens of stages it has come into existence. In addition, injunctions from a variety of Dharma sutras, Grityasutras and Smriti nibandhana – all such do’s and don’ts incorporated into the others, already mentioned. These set forth spiritual, secular, family and societal conduct. Based on these Sruti (Super/Non human scriptures and smrities (sayings of incarnations of God as in Bhagavadgita and the wise works of sages and saints), the Ramayana and Mahabharata have given a definite direction to the life of our people. The Vedangas or branches or off-shoots of the Vedas like the fine arts of music and architecture have been refining the mental attitude of people. Even the social forces separated from Sruti and Smriti including the questions and problems arising from them have been pictures history, myth and legend and literature. New attitudes, modes of thought and moral standards have been born and come into vogue. Thus the primary substance for Hindu culture has been the sum total of Veda, the Dharma Sastras, History, Myth and Legend, Tradition and respect for the holy sages and saints. Within this vast complex of basic, original culture have arisen many regional and class cultures. India is a very vast country, isn’t it? From the Himalayas to Rameswaram, from Kolkata to Mumbai, the quality of the land and the air changes every fifty miles. Within the Mysore State there is a considerable difference in the customs of Hassan and Kolar. In addition to the nature-born external differences, there are language differences, caste, religion and creed differences, differences in conduct and habits have also been born. As a result of this, within the fold of Hindu society there are hundreds of regional and class distinctions creating weales within weales and though not in mainstream culture, in certain aspects is manifold. In addition to all this, in the last one thousand years the influence of the Muslim religions and practices, education and culture have mingled. For hundreds of years the Arab and Parsee influence of people of foreign countries – is seen in literature, music and architecture on Hindu life. After that came the Western influence. Here influence of various sciences that came with Christianity and English literature are important. The functions of the scientific disciplines took the shape of – asking questions like “How is that?” “Why is this?” and opening up a questioning attitude, encouraging freedom of thought, conducting research through novel examinations and new thought to discover sources of the power of nature, acquiring new machines and through them increasing social comforts, inspiring social reformation etc. The necessity for our sage-like intuition to mix with the modern achievements in science has arisen. Thus Indian culture has been growing through a thousand influences.

Generally the culture of all countries is similar. In England, in addition to their natural native tradition has joined the influence of the cultures of Greece, Rome, France and Germany and the influence of the various categories of Christianity and finally the social changes brought about by the contact with India. Thus the result of various types of origins are unceasing characteristic of culture.

A very important fact in human history is that in the last 300-400 years the distance between various countries has diminished and a mutual contract constantly increasing. In these interactions of the peoples, each country and each section of society has many palaces which are multi-storeyed with dozens of doors and windows wide open, and receiving light and breeze from all directions spreads out their perfume in every direction. It is the opinion of Mahatma Gandhiji that we should look upon other cultures with an understanding eye, incorporate certain select aspects into ours and augment the uniqueness of our rich heritage.

“I do not want my house to be walled in on all sides, nor my windows to be shut. I want the cultures of all lands to blow about my house as freely as possible; but I refuse to be blown off my feet by any of them. I refuse to live in other people’s houses as an interloper, a beggar or a slave”.

-M.K. Gandhi

Great rivers like Ganga and Brahmaputra while flowing absorb tens of small rivers on the way and the waters are seen from a myriad directions near the ocean. Like that river, culture has one source at birth, in a life’s progress many; origin is one but in modification and transformation world-wide.

Culture is like an ancient banyan tree. It fixes itself in the ground in the space of a couple of yards thus comparatively in a limited area. But its head rears up sending forth branches and sub-branches spreading forth in all directions reaching out towards the sky sucking forth succor from the air from all winds and gives shelter to thousands of all varieties of birds. If the level of the roots it is firmly fixed, at the level of its head is unlimited and free. Culture is also like that. As its origin it is monocentric, belonging to a single society, a single country. But at the level of yielding fruit in its effect, it is many splendoured and formed out of many societies, extremely extensive. It connects the particular and individual with the universal and the general. Its one end is the individual, the other end is the whole world. It spreads from the limited to the unlimited. Thus culture, starting as it does with a single source – a single society and a people – as it keeps on growing, it incorporates into itself the essence of the entire universal experience, becomes a separate wealth. Thus culture is a combination of the individual and universal.

We have perceived above what the inner essence of Indian culture is – (1) The sublime level of the Self (2) From that vantage point the order and levels of the four goals of life (3) Consequent order in keeping with Dharma – These three are the foundational concepts of Indian culture. The necessity to accommodate these in the various foreign elements is a necessity that has been recognized by everyone in our country now. This Endeavour of integration is by no means easy, because the value system of the westerners and others is fundamentally different from that of Indian standards. The supremacy of the self which we uphold is not generally seen in their conduct of worldly affairs. They give the first priority to creature comforts and the means of obtaining them, not to the realization of the Self as we do in our culture. Even in this we and they are mutual opposites in a way. But still worldly contact has become unavoidable. We cannot give up completely the influence of Europe and America; we cannot condemn them as being intrinsically bad. We have to accept that there are many agreeable aspects in them. This being the case, while incorporating those other cultures into ours, we have to determine their merits and defects from our point of view. The enjoyment-oriented freedom of the Western countries, the alround equal opportunities for the common man, the democratic ideal, the ultimate judgment of society and its acceptance – all these aspects must be re-examined by the Indians in the light of their view of self-Realization, and its ultimate value and importance. This is a job which can be accomplished by a committee of wise men taking their own time and it cannot be done by ordinary common men and in an emotional state and through argument.

[Now if you entertain any doubts in matters of duty or conduct, you should watch carefully how the discriminating intellectuals, upright people, people who are dedicated to truth, those who have conquered anger and other excessive emotional states and those Brahmins who have established themselves firmly in Dharma – you have to follow their example].

To sum up, every Indian, while adopting foreign institutions and traditions, if he doesn’t blindly imitate them in everything and remember distinctly the principle “There is such a thing as an Indian view: All changes and difference must be such that they do not clash with our Indianness” – if they act according to this principle, then the synthesis of our own and Western modes might be beneficial to us and bring benefits to the world.

Worldly Progress

A possible misinterpretation has to be avoided here. There is absolutely no contradiction between worldly progress and self cultivation. Among the original ingredients of culture is science; The study of scriptures and the cultivation of art is another part. The knowledge of various natural and social sciences and the attainment of the principle of creation according to scripture is one aspect; another is the awareness of inner reality obtainable by experience of literature and art. The structure that arises on the foundation of these two aspects of truth is culture. There is place in it for inner peace just as much as for the achievement of mental satisfaction and also for providing the means of creature comforts. Culture does not reject worldly wealth; it is all for it; but within certain limits and in a particular order. Culture does not say no to this worldly comforts and scientific achievement; in fact it asserts its necessity. But it says that science must integrate with artistic and philosophical truth, and not shine by itself. Culture does not object new changes in society; it says that it is necessary; but it demands that the new should come a part of the age-old mainstream. Culture doesn’t reject anything good; it says that all kinds of good are essential. But it says that everything must harmoniously blend in a proper manner and be absorbed mutually.

Who is a cultured Man?

The characteristics of a cultured man are basically five:

The knowledge of one’s own place in the world.
Our actions – An understanding how it affects others.
Self-control.
An integrated view.
Simplicity.

Morals (“Neeti”)

At the conceptual level all these are aspects of our morals and ends or goals. Here the word “Neeti” means that which can bring us our intended goal – that which can get us our obtainable objective. Smoothness, politeness, justice – all these are forms of morals. It is a means of bringing two people together. At one end there is the intender, at the other the intended object or individual. The action at one end reaches out to the other end. Thus the personalities of both these individuals according to this method will be moving always from here to there and back from there to here. Therefore each individual action that man performs in society, each quality that he shows will have its effect in two places. One pertains to the doer, the other to the person affected. When a man tells a lie it shunts and twists the soul of the speaker. It deceives another person. Thus our actions and evil actions affects in two ways. One of them is Self-regarding; The other is world-regarding. That behaviour which is beneficial to both is moral. Truthfulness, cleanliness, non-violence, non-covetousness, generosity, control of senses – these are moral principles mutually beneficial. A person who follows these things is pure and develops his inner strength and at the same time does justice to co-workers without being a cheat or being unjust.

For this kind of dual moral principle, the origin is a respectful attitude. First of all he must have self-respect. A man must maintain a high level in his speech and actions. He must feel within himself a lacuna if he deviates even an inch from this conduct. He must never give room for any situation where he has to feel ashamed about any of his actions even while not being observed by anyone. He must not feel that he is mean even in his own eyes. Thus a man who has confidence in his own integrity of his conscience has self-respect. How can a man without it respect others?

The second one is the respect he must have in respect of the world. Just as a person has his own individuality, just as he has his own rights and responsibilities – don’t the others too? There is a necessity of giving respect to them also. Just as he should not embarrass his own soul, he must not give room for other’s souls to get embarrassed. To provide strength without hindering the flowering forth of the just desires of others and without hampering their self-respect is the second part of the moral principle.

Thus in our worldly affairs acting with the two – fold interest of oneself and others, in a mutually beneficial way is moral behavior. When once the moral foundation is strong and firm what can rest on it are the manifestations and decorations of culture.

The Knowledge of One’s Own Place in the World

A cultured man will be always searching for an appropriate place for himself in his world. It is certain that each living being has its own place in the world order. But which is that place? Every man has the difficulty of finding out its limits and limitations. Here a little experience may be given as an example. It happened when I was a small boy. In order to ward off the evil effects of the cholera disease which had invaded our village, some friends had arranged a bhajan (singing of songs in praise of God) on every Saturday. The bhajan would take place by turns in various houses. On the day on which our turn came, big carpets had been spread in the living room, bright kerosene lamps had been lit and in addition to that on all four sides oil lamps in artistic metal holders were kept and the entire house had been cleaned up and beautifully decorated. In the centre of the hall, facing the door were placed the large framed pictures of Gods which were decorated with flower garlands. In the central portion of the hall a low table had been put covered by a nice cloth and on it were arranged silver plates with flowers, sandal incense and coconuts. Agarbathis, pleasant smelling incense sticks were exuding sweet scent. I had also seen packets of sugar and dried coconut pieces being made, along with areca nuts folded in betel leaves – This “prasadam” to be distributed after the chanting was over. It was but natural that in my mind enthusiasm was springing forth after seeing all this. In that celebration I and my two friends were sitting near the table right at the centre wearing good clothes. That was the time when the bhajan group would arrive at our house from the temple. The group were just about to step in. Then my grandfather came into the hall to see if the arrangements were alright. The moment he saw me he rushed to me pulled me up and quickly took me to a corner and sat me down. Then a dialogue turned between him and an elderly friend of his:

Friend : He is just a child; let him sit there.

Grandfather : Let him stay; but let him stay in a place fit for him.

Friend : He is the master of the house. Let him stay where he likes.

Grandfather : Yes; he is the master, that is why he must make room for guests and he must stay in the background.

Friend : Can he know all this at this young age? Grandfather : No he can’t; but we can. We must teach.

I don’t remember that I got deflated and wanting in any way when my grandfather did this. After the Bhajan was over and guests had departed, when we were having our dinner, my grandfather talked to me affectionately and said, “child, when you go to a gathering you must know what your place is and stay there”. That is intelligent behaviour. You can know the worth of a clerk by where he places his ink-pot. Similarly when a man is visiting, you can see what kind of man he is by observing the place he chooses to sit. My grandfather added things like “When you sit nobody should say – Don’t sit there” etc. (Nobody should think that such bits of advice have had an effect on me). That advice applies to the large world also. On account of the history of our family, our birth, our educational achievement, our looks and behaviour and also our good fortune – these will have determined our place in society. Along with what is due to us, the rights and honours that are due to others will also have been incorporated in the way we are treated. The understanding of the mutual agreements between us and the others, this knowledge must determine what we should not exceed where we should diminish ourselves in our social conduct. The place determines the responsibility. After comprehending one’s own responsibility, the proper behaviour in keeping with it. On the one hand it is the practice of smooth and gentlemanly behaviour. On the other the flowering forth of one’s strength and ability. Thus the development of man’s capacity in belonging to the world.

Realizing where one belongs is the mother of the knowledge of one’s duty. In whatever given circumstances on duty is defined by our own inclinations and strength on the one hand and the wellbeing of our surrounding neighbours’ desires and hopes. This is the concept of one’s own dharma – “Swadharma”. The loss between what is external and what is internal is minimized through acting in a manner that maximum benefits are obtained. This manner of conduct is dharma. When an individual looks at dharma from the point of view of special circumstances, that is his “swadharma”. From one’s own position comes his “swadharma”.

It is common knowledge that many of the ills of our world is because of some people in society trying to aspire for positions beyond their merit and some others occupying important positions and not doing anything to acquire the necessary qualifications afterwards. When a man worth a rupee behaves like a man worth two rupees, the experience of society is like the experience of a man who pushes into his mouth a Marcel of food which is too big for his mouth. That is a tradition of uselessness. There is another kind of preposterousness which is the opposite of this. That is also special with us. That is, a two- rupee worth object. Politeness need not descend to the level of self effacement. Our modesty should not go that far as to make others feel embarrassed. When a man goes to a gathering is well known the people will have an idea where he should sit. If, instead of going there, he exhibits modesty by self abnegation, to the extent to which he pretends, the people also exhibit exaggerated respect towards him. The result is that the lookers on will be disgusted. When a man goes to an assembly of people, he must not draw attention to himself either through his dress code or outlandish behaviour. It is the characteristic of a gentleman to mix with them unobtrusively like sugar in milk or rhythm in music. The main consideration should be not to rock the boat by upsetting the general pattern with his own difference. When a man visits another also, it is the same principle. Just as we expect a certain code of conduct from them, they also expect it from us. That is just. Our apparel and conversation must follow that code. The freedom that does not respect others is actually vanity.

Our Understanding of the Suggested Desires of Others

Just now a word has been said about external circumstances. The important aspect of it is the knowledge of other’s intentions which are left unspoken. We must be thinking constantly about the effect of what we do on others. Only the belief that our intention is good does not make our conduct beneficial. We must guess the attitude of others in relation to our intended actions.

[Even a cow can understand what we communicate either by our speech or by the expression of the eye. Horses and elephants carry the burdens hoisted to their backs without being told to do so. He is wise who knows what to do by intelligent guesswork and not by a verbal order. The knowledge of merely suggested meaning is the mark of wisdom].

There is no greatness in doing what the others ask us to in so many words. We may act according to their wishes after they have literally, verbally expressed themselves either by a sense of obligation or because of the fear of displeasing them, or by making them feel obliged to us or any other reason apart from knowing their mind. The satisfaction arising in others as a result of this is not of the first degree. They get a superior sort of satisfaction by our action of knowing their unexpressed mental desires. Those others remain tight-lipped on account of a delicate sensibility and don’t openly express their desires may even feel hurt by our crude and selfish actions, unaware of their wants.

Thus in order to understand what actions may please or displease others, one must place oneself in their position. The aforesaid knowledge of one’s own place must be conjoined with their position. A cultured man is he who asks himself questions like “If I was in their position how discreet would I be? What would I perhaps do? What would be the right thing to do?”

A cultured man is he who is constantly questioning himself “How would you feel if the others did to you what you want to do to them? If they spoke about you as you have about them. What would happen to you?” Our sacred texts – Sruti, Smriti and Puranas are full of this message.

These are the words of Isavasyopanishat

[He who sees all living in himself and himself in all living beings, he is without attachment and fear].

-Bhagavadgita – 6-29

[Himself in all beings and everyone in himself].

-Bhagavadgita – 6- 32

[As if he is everywhere he acts with a sense of equality].

-Apastambha Smriti

[All beings as oneself].

Such statements are found in a hundred places in the Apastambha Smriti. The Mahabharata and the Smriti Literature abound in such sentences.

-Devala Smriti

[A man who should not do to others what is not good for himself].

-Dakshya Smriti

[He who desires good for himself must see others as he sees himself. Happiness and sorrow for the others will be the same as in his own case].

Thus in man’s mutual relationships what brings out pleasantness is the empathy arising and of equating himself with others. What makes for lack of interest is the neglect of the consideration for others. If the joints and wheels of this machine called the world have to run smoothly, silently without creating and croaking and rubbing against each other, then the greasy oil must be flowing freely which is the oil of brotherly feeling and mutual understanding. This kind of unification and integration of one with the others is possible with the pre-requisite of the expansion of the feelings of fraternity. With this flowing of the feeling of oneness between self and others the knowledge of the unspoken thoughts of others becomes possible. This is what has been referred to earlier as “Atmaupamya” in the Bhagavadgita (6-32). The means to achieve this are looking straight at Truth, the discriminating worldly wisdom and contemplation of the Ultimate Reality.

The more a person perceives the depth of human nature, the more a person contemplates on the trials and tribulations of man, when he sees the frailties and foibles of man, what he experiences is not anger but compassion. He cannot criticize too severely the little desires and constrictions. Tolerance, generosity, forgiveness, these are the qualities of paramount importance that a cultured man has cultivated. When he encounters a mistake, he imagines himself in that position and acts accordingly.

The words of an old man who passed away recently may be recollected here. That is something which I know as a direct witness. The old man in question had lived a good life. Because of some unavoidable family reasons he had to sell his house. The people who bought it had a comfortable dwelling place. The man who sold it had to use that road quite frequently. If he met the man who owned the house now, he would make polite enquiries whether he had found happiness in it. Once the new owner invited the old man into the house. He begged the old man with genuine devotion, “Please come, in, see the place and give us your blessing”. He did not agree to go inside. He said “Please don’t compel me”. The owner stopped the invitation right there and kept quiet. After the old man walked a bit further his grandson who was with him asked him “Why did you say so?” The answer of the old man was this “Child, if I had entered the house, would not old memories come crowding in? - How nice is the house now, which was once ours! Thoughts like what a pity we could not retain it would arise and may be it would have given rise to envy! Is it a good thing? It is possible some evil would come their way! Why should we give room to such bad things? May God protect them. Why should our misfortune affect them?” This is the attitude of cultured people.

(3) Self Control

The way to facilitate the others desires, is through self- control. The selfishness that is hidden within and will be taking hundreds of subtle forms. It will be emanating deceiving our knowledge. No matter how hard we try to hide our desires of ambitions like amassing wealth either in cash or kind, the intense fondness for the object of our desire, the hankering after power, the drive for fame, our actions controlled by them will be quite obvious for others. At least once in a way, when the others object to it, we will realize it to some extent. At least to the extent that man wants to hide them by protesting that he doesn’t have such defects – to the extent of not showing those traits – he will have a sense of shame.

Even more latent than these vain desires which rear their heads sometimes, there are certain pet attachments. We parade them by giving nice names like justifiable pride, partiality to merit, excellence of mind, etc. If our little child utters a fond word, if it does something smart, we feel that we ourselves have done it and broadcast it to the whole world that it can bring about universal admiration. If they start praising the cleverness of their own children, we have no patience to listen to it. We call it a “bore” – a bane. We are great, our child is not like that of others; we are special people – This illusion will be hiding in the depths of our hearts.

Similarly, the illusion that we are not like the others takes the form of casual conversation. In daily life, every man will find an occasion when he has to speak about others. Some people will be creating such circumstances themselves in addition to existing situations. In such cases, the critical comments on others’ merits and defects will be taking place with great enthusiasm. Like a goldsmith weighing an ornament in a balance, we put the other’s characters in a balance. Then if someone asks “Why are you interested so much in others?” We reply that “Such judgment of merits and de-merits are in the interests of the world”. We hesitate to admit that by de-bunking the greatness of others we derive a sort of satisfaction in our lives. We forget to ask ourselves who gave us the authority to sit in judgment over the character of others. Usually the people in public life who come to power behave as if fate has immersed them with the authority of the job “you go and improve the world”. If they don’t have such a self-confidence, their job cannot be carried out with enthusiasm. But the same self-confidence when it transgresses carefulness becomes the course for injustice on account of over- confident showmanship. As a matter of course, every member of society will have a responsibility, at least to some extent of sitting in judgment over other people’s actions. However, only to the extent to which it is absolutely necessary without overstepping the limit of its duty does a cultured man indulge himself in assessing the merits of others – and reducing the harshness to the maximum extent possible, confining oneself to the limits of one’s duty – that is the caution of the man of culture.

In a democracy – in a set up where the man who is supposed to be the representative of the country has the power of making laws – the culture which takes the form of giving up the ego may not find much encouragement. Nobody gives way to a person who thinks that his knowledge is limited and abilities are modest and stays back can find a place. Only a fellow who is a go-getter and pushes around and elbows others out will find a place in democracy. This politics of the people will blunt all the niceties of human nature and roughens them.

Thus selfishness works in various ways in our nature. Secretly, openly, directly, deviously, openly, indirectly – it will be working all the time in all sorts of ways. It cannot be said that it is evil in all circumstance. Just as it has possibilities of injustice it can also work in just ways. So what we have to desire here is not the total destruction of selfishness, not a complete cessation of it but only its orderly control. Selfishness must be tempered. Let there be self-interest; but let it be within limits, let it work, but let it work under control. Let the principle of righteousness determine its ways and means.

(4) An Integrated View

Integration or synthesis means a co-operative endeavour. It is everyone’s experience that in every question, differences of opinion do exist, but when they raise their head, because of them there should be no harm done either to individual friendship or to the unity of society. To see this happening, we must examine the various views, put together their veracity and arrange them in a mature manner. Synthesis is this kind of orderly adjustment. Bhagavan Vedavyasa has decreed it especially with regard to the beliefs of other faiths. That policy of integration deserves to be applied to politics, economics, commerce, matters of law and to all aspects of human activity. No single faith possesses all virtues and complete truth; We have to examine each argument with patience and sympathy; what is gleaned from it and to whatever extent, we must integrate with similar virtues in other points of view. For human values to rise to the maximum height, such a synthesizing process is the only means. Among the types selfishness, man’s love of his own faith is one. ‘Faith’ means opinion, belief, feeling. One’s own faith does not merely mean what we have inherited from our forefathers and from our surrounding society only and its values; The expression “one’s own faith” indicates all opinions about all subjects. This clinging to one’s own beliefs is the root cause for all disputes and quarrels. Very often when we are talking to friends we say “Didn’t I tell you this that day itself?” or “I have been saying this right from the beginning!” We have such faith in our own intellectual convictions. Many self-styled world-teachers and leaders of men have greater attachment to their brain-children than to their actual physical children born to them. This excessive attachment is the root of all astheistic arguments.

(5) Lopsided View, not correct

Many years ago in North of our country there was a holy man called “Lavanananda Swamy” (Lavana in Sanskrit means salt). His view was “Salt is the penacia in the world; if you keep eating salt, all diseases will disappear. No other medicine is of any use”. Similarly there are some devotees of Lord Sri Rama. No matter what mistake you have committed. No matter what your desires, if you just utter the two syllabals “Ra” and “Ma” all your sorrows will vanish and all your desires will come true. This is the argument of the devotees of Lord Rama. Such a poet has said:

[In the forest, the hunters (the Sanskrit-speaking ones!) were going about saying:-”Let us move about in the forest. (“Charama” means “moving around” and the sound “rama” is contained in that word. Let us rob the things – jewels and clothes – of the travelers “Apaharana” means “steal” but has “rama” in it. Then we will cross the river. “Tarama”s meaning “cross over” has the word “rama”. Then we will have no fear. “Na smaramah” meaning “no fear” has the letters “rama”. Thus when they traversed, because the word “rama” was attached in the words they used, they attained Liberation].

This is a travesty of devotion of Lord Rama. This stanza may be admired because of the clever use and repetition of the word. But where is the devotion to Sri Rama in these words? Is a sincere and genuine devotion seen here? And, for Liberation mere devotion without self-knowledge enough? Should there not be a synthesis of discrimination and practice of it there?

The trust in salt of Lavanananda and the trust in the holy name of Sri Rama – such trust are the slogans of many of our political and social reformations. “Ahimsa is the invincible weapon;” “There is no way but Khadi way (the hand-woven cotton fabrics)”; “Better anarchy than slavish compulsions” “Those who don’t want industrialization will have to go a begging in the streets”. Such ear splitting street slogan shouting shatters the very atmosphere of our times. There may be a grain of truth in these. It there no taste in salt? Is there no merit in the chanting of the Lord’s name? But in addition to the presence of limited good, there will also be attached a great deal of lack of any merit. In all human languages blunders and bloomers exist inevitably. Only through multiple perspectives it is possible to avoid them. Whether it is something said by Mahatma Gandhi or by Jinnah, no matter how big a man he is, unless it is subjected to independent scrutiny, it cannot be accepted. No matter from what mines gold has come, unless it is tested by fire, it does not become pure.

Maharshi Manu has said even about the pronouncement of a sage:

[Only that which remains good grain after having been filtered in the fine perforated pan of faultless logic is Dharma; not the rest].

The same opinion has been justified and defended by the famous commentator Kullukabhatta through an ancient pronouncement.

- Manu 12 – 106 -Manu. 12 – 113.

When there is a necessity in the case of the Scripture itself, what is there to say about the views of human beings? In our times, the facilities and conveniences for the propaganda of religion and faiths have increased to an unprecedented extent. The printing machines are in abundance; paper is cheap; the telephones, newspapers and platforms are a plenty which instead of increasing awareness are augmenting noisy controversies. The singing of the praises of Rama are a balm to the ear; Rama’s banishment to the forest is intolerable even to imagine. So people go to the easy bhajans of Rama; the vow of Rama is not even recollected. It is natural to understand what is easy. The newspapers and the leaders of men prepare their pills of panacea, put them in attractive bottles with catchy labels pasted on them and sell their ideas. It is easy for people to swallow these pills. It is difficult to examine their composition. People do what is easy. Thus atheistic philosophies and perverse arguments have sprung up in the world. It is on account of this that there is envy among various groups; enimity between nations; from this comes the jealousy between castes and wars among people.

It has already been mentioned earlier that in matters of opinion stubbornness is improper. Truth has a thousand forms. The proper application with taste and finesse of these take ten thousand shapes. Therefore to insist that one question has only one answer is far from truth. To get from one place to another one can’t have a straight road as the crow flies. The straight road may be full of pitfalls and difficult to negotiate. It may look like a shortcut but in fact may be a circuitous one. The path that looks distant for the eye may actually be quite close to the feet to walk across. Thus if anyone asks “which is the nearest route from Mysore to Bangalore, two or three answers will have to be given according to the questions – “for whom?” and “in what vehicle?” Depending on each condition different answers are correct. In all human dealings, a single definite, final answer “this is so” cannot be given at all. Such being the case, wherever there are such differences of opinion each one should adopt a conciliatory tone and say in a compromising way “could be”, “It could be that way too”. Then the aspects of differences between various opinions will decrease and points of agreement will increase. In today’s world the argumentative good manners is missing. All people will be attached to a particular point of view, and will take a strong fanatical position. It is these fanatical following and strong allegiances that are mainly responsible for the turmoils of the present day world. If the world should give up these extremes and become a friendly place, this diplomatic “may be” attitude must be taught and that culture should spread.

Man’s life, like the confluence of rivers like Ganga and Brahmaputra contains the hundreds of powers and speeds getting merged. This great conflict is as interesting as natural. That interest in the confluence is when man barricades and bridges their different speeds and gives it a certain direction. That is culture. That is diplomacy in dealing with worldly affairs. That is the light which pleasantly lights up life. There are hundreds of things which we want moment by moment in our lives. The Sruti itself has said “Asmin loke bahavaha kamaha” (Taithiriya 3 Br 13 – 9) which means that there are many desires in the world. Culture is that which informs us which will have to be obtained to what extent to be within limits should be eschewed to avoid excess.

In a kingdom the agriculturists inform what is good for them and request that it should be given to them. The merchants know what is beneficial to them and demand it. The city dwellers look to their comfort. The villagers beg for their conveniences. If you look at them separately, each demand looks just. But there is a greater entity, above and beyond all these, encompassing all these and many more entities. That is the country. Keeping that totality in mind and its good, doing justice to all sections without hindering the progress of the others is the efficiency of the minister. When a garland of many jewels worn by different parties, are sewn together through a thread of synthesis passing through all of them and making the whole thing into a single garland – that is the man who is politically astute. That which we call right taste in the proper proportionate blending of salt, sour etc. in cooking, that which we call melody in music which is an integration of sruti and laya (sound and tempo), that which we call proportionate representation of various parts in a statue, that which we call a diplomatic policy of dissolving differences of various kinds in administration, such a creation of synthesis which is satisfactory, such a self-controlled behaviour, such a universally beneficial, genuine, enlightened originality is what is called culture.

What is prefatory to synthesis is the decision regarding priorities. Among the myriad things we want, there is not a single one which is unnecessary; but there should be a fixed order of priorities in their importance. Some come first. Some later. This relative position is the basis for synthesis. Determining the value of various things and arranging them in steps, from the point of view of ultimate value of inner importance is the synthesizing principle. That is the organization of our desires and duties. There is nothing unjustly treated; nothing gets greater importance than what it deserves.

Cleansing Policy

The cultured individual has the same cleansing attitude regarding the clinks and quirks of the world and adopts the same technique as a good surgeon does regarding a sick patient who is suffering from a disease pertaining to a particular organ. The surgeon may have to resort to the use of knife and scissors in order to set right the diseased growth of flesh in the stomach, or untangle a knot of nerves or cure the sore of the bone. But he first thinks “Can’t it be set right without an operation?” Until his conscience says that it is unavoidable, he cannot touch his instruments. And after he has decided to operate he prepares methods like “chloroform” in order to assuage the pain to the patient and takes every precautionary measure. When it becomes absolutely impossible to avoid pain, he tries to reduce the pain to the maximum extent possible. And then cuts off the minimum portion of the nerve or the bone. He doesn’t remove even an iota more than necessary. He will be all the time concerned lest he should over act. He cures the wound in the earliest possible time after the operation.

A cultured man doesn’t approve the quirks and the perversities in the behaviour of the people around him. But he doesn’t impatiently interfere either with the course of reforming them. He is always engaged in the endeavour of correcting himself; and correcting his near and dear ones. But in that process of correction there is no crudeness. He doesn’t shout about his own stubborn convictions; his face doesn’t show him with red, inflamed eyes and the grinding teeth. When it becomes absolutely unavoidable for him to register his dissent he shows only the force and power that are just enough and never shouts raising his voice. With his discourse and conduct he makes the disagreemnt unobtrusive.

A truly cultured man acts as a mother does when she is punishing her child or when a faithful wife corrects her husband. He answers with a friendly attitude. The loud – mouth response of the others doesn’t make him shout about; the contorted faces of others doesn’t take away his pleasantness. If the main characteristic of culture is to be summarized in a nutshell it is “lack of crudeness”. A certain amount of strength becomes necessary in worldly dealings. Some occasions do arise when the voice has to be raised. A man cannot always remain a ball of butter or a lump of jaggery. It doesn’t always make for righteousness. Dharma or right conduct itself demands bravery and uncompromising attitude sometimes. In such circumstances the cultured person doesn’t go haywire and becomes hard, just as hard as is justifiable in order to set right the world. The cane of the schoolmaster is sharp at one end and affectionate at the other end. The hardness of the cultured man is just such. There is no roughness, no perversity, no self forgetfulness in it. In everything his is a smooth way, a delicate step. A strict behaviour without ostentation, a slap that doesn’t hurt.

Elegant Simplicity

Above all, a sense of proportion – humour – elegance – simplicity which means an attitude which searches for what renders anything interesting and bringing it out, it is very rare indeed when there are no bad qualities and seeds of sorrow in human situations. In whatever we see in our daily life the sorrowful content predominates. The cultured individual searches for beauty inquisitively in the midst of this mess. He searches for pleasantness in the midst of bitter circumstances. When misfortune lands him in a desert, instead of being enveloped by depression, he doesn’t stand resourceless but searches for a cool “oasis”. That is his nature. He is one who searches for a footpath in a dark forest, who wide-eyed, looks out for a lantern-light in a village hut in the forest of the night. This is the quality which our ancestors have called the capacity to see good. It seems the swan can separate milk from water in water-mixed milk, takes only milk and rejects the water. It seems Lord Parameshwara, when both the moon and poison came out of the ocean, put the moon on this head and retained the poison in his throat to prevent it from affecting others. This partiality for good and rejecting evil is the mark of good taste. A cultured man retracts his mind’s eye in all circumstances from inauspicious things and directs his gaze on the auspicious which may be hiding behind the other. He tries to instill the hope of light in the hearts of the depressed with darkness. In the midst of people whose faces are taut and tight-lipped he says something humorous to relax their mood. In a lackluster situation he will create an opportunity for laughter. He will turn our attention from the dried up bark and branches of a tree to fresh sprouts and towards green buds. He believes that the fresh will be behind the stale, that green lurks behind a fossil and this is so always, everywhere. He is a man with a heart. In him will be swelling forth the essence of human love, the essence of sympathy and compassion and the essence of friendship. As a result of the efficacy of that elixir all his bark and all his moral principles will be felt as salutary by the people. That refinement and that beauty is what renders human life attractive. That is the inner essence of culture.

Even in simple enjoyment there is a question of propriety. He (the cultured person) will also have his share of joy and sorrow like the others. But he doesn’t broadcast the depth and width of those experiences. When he sees the petals of a flower opening up, his mind also might open up and eyes beam. But his hand doesn’t stretch forth to pluck it. When his efforts bring forth victory and triumph his heart may respond and his lips part. But its sound doesn’t break forth beyond the line of these teeth. In his laughter there is no laughtiness; in his pride there is no vanity. Even when he picks up and fondles his child, he looks this way and that. Because he doubts whether it will affect somebody’s mental equilibrium. That kind avoidance of excess – that kind of self-control – is the hallmark of culture. It is good manners which doesn’t ask for fame, it is a happiness that doesn’t make noise.

The world-machine is a very big one. Its wheels and joints are in hundreds. If these things have to turn smoothly without a creaking and cracking noise and stop altogether, its wheels and joints must be well oiled now and then, quite constantly, infact. That smoothening oil is culture. With his moral devices which are consigned by his sophisticated vision, with his balanced and friendly policies of behaviour – the burden of our life will be lightened at least to the extent of bearability, the tiresomeness of the journey will be forgotten. Culture is the architectural device which makes the road smooth the path for the chariot of Dharma.

A Man of Taste

The man of taste is a citizen of the kingdom of mind. The mind is not outside the body. Therefore the world of the body is not far away for the man of taste. The commerce of the mind is only through the body. Though this is the case of the main focus of the man of taste is more on the workings of the mind rather than those of the body

Let us look at an example. Among the acts of commission pertaining to the body and the mind, the most direct and famous is eating. Hunger is natural to all living beings. Everyone wants a meal. But there are two kinds. (1) One uncultivated (2) A man of cultured taste. The ordinary man wants his stomach full. For the man of taste not only does he want to fill his stomach but he desires a perfume to envelop his mouth. For the common man quantity is important, for the man of taste quality.

All young ladies want to wear flowers in their braids. For the uninitiated “sevantige” flowers – and a load of them; for the sophisticated, “jasmine”, just one or two.

The ordinary man eats and belches himself to sleep. The cultured waits for scent, flowers and music. The satisfaction of the uninitiated is in the body; that of the man of taste is in the mind.

What is eaten, seen, heard and enjoyed are important for the body. Thus says the uninitiated. The man of taste wants it to untaste into the mind and permeate the soul of man.

Culture not by Books Alone

In our country culture is a very ancient concept. It is anterior to book learning. Earlier than modern European civilization took root here, highly cultured people who were not literate were found in abundance. If any person had to be complemented, he would be called a “sabhya” or a well-behaved, upright, soft- spoken person. This fit for assembly – fitness for cultivation in society – was culture. In the villages, the illiterate agriculturists, shepherds and potters were not lacking in culture. They knew very well the difference between the just and the unjust, between the big and the small, the proper and improper conduct and behaviour. The so-called educated people, when there were disputes and differences of opinion among them, would invite these non-literate upright men and respect their decision. Thus it is clean that there is no inevitable connection between book learning and cultured right conduct

How did culture spread so widely then? Our ancestors seemed to have understood the nature and pathways of the true essence of culture. Three or four aspects are important here.

Culture is a living entity. It grows by itself life a plant, like a child. It is not like a machine manufactured product.
Like a flower in a plant, from inside man it comes out after growing. It cannot be pushed in. It is not like the ornament fixed from outside.
It is pervading in all areas of life like a perfume. It is not seen only in one or two parts, being absent elsewhere.
It does not come into existence because of our hurry. It takes its own time. It won’t do if we want to speed up the process of child’s teething, talking, and walking. Culture is acquired according to the inner propensity, intellect and preparedness of each individual.

Culture is the fruit of the general development of society and it occurs by itself – like the strength of the body – when the food and the sporting habits are alright, the strength is self- acquired. There is no need for any special effort. A characteristic of health is strength. Similarly if the organization of learning and education is proper, culture grows by itself. A separate propaganda for it is unnecessary. Our ancestors had found this out. They knew that indirect influence was more fruitful than direct propaganda. This is the reason why they established the indirect influence in every aspect of life through stories, poetry, music architecture and aesthetic appeal. The varied popular cultural arts and activities like bhajans, narration of puranas, gospels like harikathas, recitation of epics, ballad-singing, various types of stage productions like Bhagavatarata, Yakshagana and drama – these were the artistic means to achieve the end of preservation of culture. Things like temples, towers and pinnacles, processions and religious gatherings performed the same function for attracting people and having a hold on them. It is the art of dissolving the artistic teaching in a tasty connection to drink. Just as in tasty rasam, health – promoting and medicinal charactered ingredients like, pepper, cardamom and other herbs and roots are mixed resulting in improved taste performs the function of digestion – doing good without our conscious knowledge – so too the fine arts, through providing aesthetic pleasure and entertainment purify them. The elevation of the spirit through engendering the memory of the sacred in the vicinity of a holy spirit is the origin of culture.

Creation of the atmosphere of spiritual elevation was the objective of our ancestors. They suspected that direct teaching and slogan-mongering might not only be fruitless but even counter-productive. Institutions like temples, charity houses, maths or monasteries and places of pilgrimage – all such institutions became the means of uplifting the minds of people from the mundane to a higher level. Ritual worship and listening to sacred myths and legends came in handy to supply courage, patience and belief in their moments of doubt. Incidentally they taught them the discrimination between the higher and the lower and a sense of humility. What else is culture? The culture of our people is the inner cultivation of the result of such virtues for thousands of years without fuss and hurry, without artificiality and without noise and fanfare. Fortitude in misfortune, partiality for justice while surrounded by injustice, contemplation of the spiritual in the midst of the secular – these are the qualities that have been the protective armor for the Hindus for thousands of years. This is not the job of publication and propaganda. It is the endeavour of natural wisdom. Our people have recognized the value of culture themselves and have accepted it. That is why culture has survived.

Prospect

The future of culture in our country is not very encouraging at present. The ideals and traditions of old have eroded to a great extent in our lives. New commitments have not yet come to us. The new culture that has come to us from Europe are only at the face value. In matters of food and recreation the old restrictions are loosening, the moral bindings of people have been shaken. The past generations believed in truth, (“Sathya”) sanctity of promises (“Niyattu”) and spiritual merit (“Punya”). Even if we say it was a superstitious belief, as a result of it one could see in their behaviour a certain strength, a certain confidence and a certain reliability. Today the fear of sin (“Papa”) is vanishing. The belief in other words and after life has withered away. Even the memory of what is called God is becoming rare. If the necessity of God is felt anywhere, it is only in selfish circumstances. Only the visible world – its momentary experience this has become the be – all of everything and the mind has become incapable of comprehending unseen truth and the eternal existence. Because of these reasons, the here and the now has become more valuable than the other – worldly and the old moral and ethical values have turned topsy – turvy.

To start with the opinion of those who learned the English alphabet became the starry – eyed brilliance. The government job and regular salary went to their heads like heady wine. Those have-nots got sand in their eyes and the merchant class joined hands with those in power, prepared for foreign trade. The arrogance of money increased. Pretty sights and table-meals wiped out the name of heaven. What the bank accepts is good fortune; what the mouth admires is happiness; what is enjoyed is what is gained; what is saved is an investment – such beliefs have been spreading among people. The money culture has overshadowed the civilization of agricultural produce.

There is yet one other factor for perturbing our minds. The scientific education brought in by the English shook the roots of our culture to a considerable extent. Let alone the condemnatory slogans indulged by the priests in conversion propaganda. More than that was the influence the sciences brought that came to us through English. This scientific probing was question – oriented. “How is that? Why is this? Where is heaven? What is the proof for the existence of God? What is the evidence for the workings of Karma? Who is the witness for re- incarnation?” Such questions eclipsed the old beliefs. But this eclipse did not spare Europe either. Even there, the old religions upheavals took place. It happened with us also. But of late there are signs of the eclipse ending there. The necessity for re- valuation and re-thinking in the re-examination of certain conclusions reacted. Therefore the danger to religious beliefs from science is decreasing. Now science does not reject religions injunctions. This is a heartening matter to those who have a confidence in the culture of the Indian sub-continent.

Is there a place for Indian culture in the present-day world? If it has to survive and grow, should it incorporate certain equations in its structural aspects? What type of things are they? Just as they are important question, they are equally complex and difficult. If the present writer attempts to answer this briefly it would take some such shape as this: That spiritual outlook, that curtailing force of sensual pleasures, that moral overview which controls excessive hoarding and acquisition instinct because of our scriptural heritage, these characteristics are necessary for the world of today. Unless all nations accept that as their own national cultural principle, there will be no peace for people and human population in general. But first of all, we must make it clear to ourselves and apply it in our daily life. Are we today in a position to tell others that they should follow our example? Wherever we look in our country today what we see is disorganization, dissatisfaction and lack of proper orientation. Along with this, we have not yet thought fundamentally about the question of how to equate our scriptural tradition with that of the West. Without spoiling the Indianness – without our nation becoming second to anyone in our strength and riches, in a way in which it is highly respected in the eyes of others, other nations, we must equate our culture once again. It is possible only through cogitation and criticisms. Manu’s words are:-

That outlook is the primary duty of the lovers of India. Through an overview is equation possible.

There will be an innate opposing force preventing culture from gaining popularity. Culture means no aspect of life becoming excessive; everything being within limits and under control. Such a limited state for most people is without excitement and tame. From this point of view there seem to be two kinds of people. Most people want speed, ostentation and passion. Only just a few desire peace and equanimity. Between Dharmaraya and Bhima, only Bhima is appreciated, preferred and clapped by ordinary folk. Those who admire Dharmaraya are few and far between. At the slightest provocation Bhima twirls his moustache. One who shouts shall I knock down a hill? Shall I drink the ocean? Shall I uproot the tree? Shall I swing my mace and fell the sun? A man who cautions, we should not act in haste; let us weigh the pros and cons; Do we in anyway transgress the righteous path? Such a person is considered a coward. One who is physically aggressive is a brave man; one who is forgiving is a weakling. This is the attitude of most people – especially the young, the well-built and the strong. For them culture is a bland food – fit only for people recovering from illness. It is only natural that it should appear so, isn’t it? Those who can appreciate culture are those who have matured with the experience of suffering. Those who have learnt their lesson of observing those who have gone astray through false enthusiasm for wrong things and immature undertakings can know the value of culture. For the rest it is not the very stuff of life but only an external embellishment.

The Words of Emerson

It has been said above, has it not, that a cultured individual keeps everything under limits as prescribed by the principle of propriety? The American philosopher, Ralph Waldo Emerson (1803-1882) has said – “Culture kills the propensity for excessive importance; it kills his pride in saying My village, my town. When we came out into the street we should leave our loving little children at home and look at the people we meet with a large – hearted discriminatory sense and politeness. No piece of work is worth its while which is done without a feeling of fraternity… The man who has attained fame as a brilliant person would have bought that fame at a great price. His head would be swollen and flying high in an ivory tower. Instead of behaving like a healthy and happy person, he will be jumping about like a madcap. The reason for this inner vanity and egoism is the extension of the external attractions. Their variety is the proper medicine. Acquaintance with the ways of the world, coming into contact with different levels of people, traveling, good medical treatment, philosophical enquiry, art, thinking of religious tenets, study of books, social concern, cultivation of being alone – these are the medicines for the natural pride of man”.

As the pride in us decreases, so does discontent; and the burden caused by us to the world also gets lessened. The mental attitude (Yoga) of lightening the weight of life is culture. This is Self-cultivation. The word “Culture in English means this inner training, the sophisticating process of the latent Self ”. All this meaning is contained in the following poem of Emerson.

Can rulers or tutors educate
The semigod whom we await?
He must be musical,
Tremulous, impressional,
Alive to gentle influence
Of landscape and of sky,
And tender to the spirit – touch
Of man’s or maiden’s eye;
But, to his native centre fast,
Shall into Future fuse the Past
And the world’s flowing fates in his own mould recast.

The Ideal Valmiki Upheld

The great poet Valmiki has upheld the ideal of culture in the shaping of the personality of Sri Ramachandra murhty:

[He is always tranquil and begins the conversation himself, and he speaks softly. (1) He does not reply roughly to those who speak roughly (2) He is happy always to remember some little favour done to him at some time (3) He never remembers a hundred injustices done to him; the reason for it being the courage and self-confidence vested in him. (4) He has sympathy for the humble; one who knows the Right Path; one who has self-control; one who is pure (5) He has wisdom according to his origin of birth; he respects the Dharma of the warrior class (Kshatriya) as being high (6) He is the repository of all virtues, fair, brave, truthful and simple (7) He has been educated in the goals of life, Dharma (Right conduct) and Artha (wealth) and Kama (desire) by Brahmins and elders. (8) He is blessed with memory power as well as brilliance. (9) He acts with tact in worldly affairs and the traditions of society (10) He has unswerving faith in God; he has firmly established sense of discriminations; he never accepts evil; never speaks evil (11) He is without laziness; never forgets himself; he is aware of the defects in himself as well as in others. (12) He is an adept in Shastras; wise to distinguish the do’s and don’ts. He is capable of surmising the inner prompting of others (13) He is capable of upholding justice in both punishing and rewarding. (14) He knows the proper time and place for earning the goodwill of people and retaining it as well as trampling down evil. (15) He is a good planner in matters of income; and careful in matters of expenditure (16) He is one who has attained a top position in both the company of the learned scholars of scripture as well as in an assembly of mixed talent. (17) One who is efficient in gathering both Dharma (spiritual merit) as well as Artha (money) and enjoying both without lethargy. (18) One who is without envy; one who has conquered anger; one without pride; one without regret (19) One who never shames any living thing; one who never yields to some momentary pressure forgetting righteousness and his own oath not to deviate from it.]

Let those who want to realize the true nature of culture contemplate on this word – picture of Lord Sri Rama described by our first poet, Valmiki.

Literature and Culture

Some Examples

Great literary works point out the beauty of cultured behaviour. Let us look at some such examples:

Rama

It is well known that when Sri Ramachandra was exiled in the forest the great sages came to him, informed him about the tortures that they were undergoing at the hands of the demons and begged him to protect them. Then, at the beginning itself, they said:

[Lord, you are a great man – One who knows Dharma and one who has love for it. We are in a position of supplicants. Therefore we have come to you and troubling you with our woes. You must excuse us.]

How does Rama reply to this humble request?

[Great sages should not make a humble request like this. Instead, they must order me. I am someone to take orders. I am obedient to them. Though my coming here had a different purpose, it is my duty to carry out your behest. My sojourn in the forest becomes meaningful from it. May my power and valour, joined with that of my younger brother, provide you an occasion for venerable sages like you to witness]

The humility of Rama, his attitude of veneration regarding the sages, his confidence in and affection for his brother, the way of assuring those who are afraid – these are to be noticed.

Sita

At the time of Rama and Lakshmana entering the Dandaka forest, they arm themselves with bows and arrows. Sitadevi entertains a doubt.

A kshatriya who is armed, like fire near the firewood becomes very potent and in that state of power may return to violence. Indra thought of disrupting the tapas (intense meditation) being performed by a sage and so he took the shape of a warrior and in that disguise gave the sage a powerful sword requesting him to keep it safe for him until he came back to reclaim it. The sage agreed and received it. Then what happened? The sage got enamored by its shine and sharpness and held it all the time, kept on using it and went to hell. The possession of weapons has that effect on the mind.

“Therefore I am afraid because you, Rama and Lakshmana are armed. You may hurt or harm animals without reason. Beware that these weapons may generate cruel thoughts in your minds. Let not the innocents be affected by you.” After Sitadevi cautions this way, she addresses her husband: “Not that you don’t know what I am telling you. I am not preaching and teaching you. I am only reminding you of what you know very well already. Prompted by the love I bear you, not to feel any lacuna in my great confidence in you and the pride I entertain in your regard, I am thus bringing it to your kind notice.”

Thus spoke Sita Devi. Observe the courtesy in this remonstration.

Lakshmana

As is well known when Sri Rama and Lakshmana came to Kishkinda, they became friends with Sugriva. Then Sugriva, on hearing the news of the loss of Rama, he informs how some time back when he and four of the vanara heroes were sojourning,they saw a demon kidnapping a lady and heard her crying out “Oh, Rama, Oh, Lakshmana” in agony and how on seeing them, she threw down to them her upper cloth and her ornaments. Not only that. He brings that apparel as well as those ornaments and places them in front of Sri Rama. He identified them as belonging to Sita and showing them to Lakshmana asks him – “Are these not hers?” Lakshmana says –

[My dear brother, I cannot recognize the bangles of sister- in-law. I have not seen them. I have never seen her ear-rings. I can recognize only her anklet, as I was prostrating at her feet every day. I haven’t lifted my head further.]

Ajatashatru

A sage by name Gargya went to a king named Ajatashatru and told him “I will teach you the nature of Parabrahmam”. The king said “Alright.” But the king was a man who knew the nature of Brahman – one who was enlightened. Gargya started mentioning the Sun, the Moon, the other luminous bodies, the powers of the great elements etc. One by one. Ajatashatru went on answering that none of them was right in the same technical terminology. Finally Gargya was defeated and he begged Ajatashatru “You yourself teach me.” But he said –

[This way, when a Brahmin goes to a Kshatriya and says “Let him teach me Brahman” is a contrary method (a topsy turvy approach) I will confess to you what it is by way of reminding you only (not with a felling that I am your Guru). Thus spoke Ajatashatru and held his hands as a friend would and got up to go elsewhere].

This is the heart of equality.

“That individual has got the mentality to protect my self- respect as he does his own.” When a man behaves that way, that is acting according to the principle of equality. It is in order to instill such a feeling that the king himself got up and made the Brahmin stand beside him by holding his hand.

And afterwards Ajatashatru Brahman.

Gopi

In order to illustrate that it is possible to learn propriety in speech through poetry, a certain poet has provided an example. Its subject matter is sorrow of separation of a Gopika. Sri Krishna has to leave for another place. He begs her to permit him to leave. Her answer is:

The poet of this poem is not known. The above thoughts are contained in the “Subhashita Ratnabhandagara” and it is mentioned as from “a man from the South” (Dakshinatya).

Culture and Nature

Some twenty or twenty five years ago, B.M. Srikantaiah made a joke. While discussing the adjustment that should exist between old tradition and new literature he provoked the audience to laugh by saying – The wife of a Brahmin is a “Brahminiti”, the wife of an “agasa” or a washerman is an “agasiti” – (These are female gender formations in the Kannada language). Similarly someone might say that the wife of “Samskrita” is “Samskriti” (“Samskrita” is the Sanskrit language and “Samskriti” means “culture”. The word “Samskriti” had come into vogue in Kannada only recently at that time. After that the use of that word has become increasingly frequent. Even the governments have felt that something called culture has value and they are giving it importance. Actually it is correct that it is a valuable thing. But what is this thing called culture?

Culture is the new name for a certain old thing. It is something that smoothens life. That is its meaning. To cultivate the virtues through which we live our lives with taste and finesse, through which the excesses like sourness and pungency are reduced and the interest in the process of life is increased, cultivation of such qualities is culture. It is a kind of education of the inner self.

In this life every individual, every moment of his existence has to have a relationship with the world, hasn’t he? What he has to take from it, the good he has to obtain from it will always be there. What he has to give to it to whatever extent will also be there. In this daily commerce of give and take, what is the best way for him to act? To search, to find out and act according to the best interests, to generate, bonhomie, to know what policy is best to be adopted, that practice is culture.

Then what is best? What is salutary? What is the nature of the good? Shall we say that what we like is best; that is the largest good? The child always wants sweets. Is it good? When we board a train to sit down, if the compartment is full and we feel like throwing a couple of people out, is it good? When we are walking in the street if the flem forms we feel like spitting it out immediately wherever we are. Is it good? Are our likes and dislikes the evidence for deciding what is good? It cannot be; because it is in everybody’s experience that the desires and tastes of people are various. Each man’s mind is his own. Therefore the ever- changing individual and personal experiences of ours cannot be taken as the principal touchstone of what is good. If our standard keeps on changing moment to moment, then it has to be one which can stand firm, unmoving and permanent. The epistemological truth must be contained in the container itself. It must stand by itself – be self-sustaining without the need for any external evidence or proof. If we can obtain a truth that is capable of spacio-temporal transcendence and common to all mankind, we can build our concept of truth on the foundation of its build our concept of truth on the foundation of its beneficial nature and salutariness. Is there such an unchanging, unmoving, eternal entity called truth? This is the fundamental question. In order to find an answer for this, we have to engage ourselves in some metaphysical speculation.

The human being who keeps on repeating “I”, “I” doesn’t have any doubt about the existence of that principle of Being, does he? An immense power, relating the individual and the world that he sees exists as the substratum for both. Many people have been calling it God from time immemorial. That same entity is also called “Paramatma” or “Parabrahman”. It is that self-same force which is making every living being say “I”, “I” and creating a connection between that and the world. All the comforts and happiness that are desired by man are but the vapours and drops of that ocean. The highest good, the greatest and ultimate goal of man is to be integrated into and become a part of that mighty ocean unlimited in its bliss. The intimate proximity of the individual soul and the absolute Self is the greatest auspiciousness. It is the ultimate goal. That code of conduct conducive to that state is good to that extent, that object which proves convenient to attain that is good to that extent, that is Dharma or right. That object or behaviour which is an impediment to this realization is bad to that extent. It is Adharma or wrong. Thus the concept or action of a man as related to the attainment of the proximity to God lies the goodness or evil. Dharma is that which determines worldly priorities from the point of view of the Realization of the absolute Self. An allotropic form of that Dharma is culture. Culture is the Dharma that has taken shape in the form of worldly contact.

Man, when he rises above innate nature is culture. The large hill at Sravanabelagola is nature; the statue of Gomateshwara on top of it is culture. The river Kaveri is nature; the paddy fields on its banks is culture. The cooked rice and sweet porridge is culture. Hair is nature; hair-styles of various kinds is culture. Cotton is nature; the sari and the dhoti are culture. Shouting is nature; singing is culture. Idle bellowing is nature; literature and drama is culture. When a child passes urine in bed, it is nature; when it comes out to do it is culture. If a man stays just as he was born, it is nature; with education and civilization he becomes cultured. Thus when human discrimination blends with nature, it is culture.

When someone points out some shortcoming of crookedness in our speech or behaviour, we are displeased and say “that’s our congenital nature. What can we do about it?” We argue as if just as we cannot change the colour of our body or our size, we cannot change our mind and minister to its quirks and contours. That argument cannot be sustained by reason or logic. Just as there are remedies to cure bodily illness, there are also medicines which can set right and cleanse mental and intellectual defects. That is culture. The important thing is that it can be achieved through human effort.

Nature is self-existent – has come into being by itself. That is “natural” or creation. It has happened by itself or come out or emanated from itself. Earth, Air, Fire-Brightness, Water and Sky these five elements are Nature. Their consequences and transformations are also Nature. The birth and death of various animals is also Nature. Their bodies and organs are also nature. Thus the entire visible world of ours in our experience and each and every object in it and their functions, are all nature. When man reacts to this world mass satisfactorily with his intellect, it becomes culture.

Then, is Man a part of nature? Is not his intellect just an aspect of that same Nature? What does it mean when it is said that he should use satisfactorily and creatively? If man’s mind is only an infinitesimal atom of the vast mountain of nature, is it possible for the atom to be superior to the enormity? Is it possible to raise the mountains and lift it with the tiny atom? Unless we cogitate on these questions, the true nature of culture cannot be mentally construed.

It is true that Man is a child of Nature, but a special sort of child. As Mathew Arnold has said-

Man hath all which Nature hath, but more,
And in that more lie all his hopes of good.
Man must begin (know this) when Nature ends;
Nature and Man can never be fast friends
Fool, if thou canst not pass her, rest her slave.

The uniqueness of Man is his creative intellect. In every thing being of the world, two things are visible, aren’t they? One is the body. The other is the life. The body is Nature. What is known as “life” is the inner activity, consciousness, not inert. The basic substance of that active entity is the self which transcends Nature. Nature takes on different forms and keeps on putting on various forms. The Self is not subject to change and remains for ever in the same state. This inner self is the essence of “life”.

The knowledge of that inner self is the uniqueness of the special creation – Man. The other animals don’t have the remembrance of the soul-stuff. Nature should have hidden the knowledge of the self in non-human animals. Even in man – Mother Nature – she would have left only a small proportion and room for self-knowledge. She would have covered up his eye – the inner eye – with a veil for twenty three hours, six days a week. A brave man who turns inwards to explore his real Self once a week for the remaining one hour may be one in a thousand!

There is a blend of three qualities (Gunas) in Nature: (1) Sattva (2) Rajas (3) Tamas. (Works like the Bhagavadgita and Manu Smriti explain their qualities). Though all these three qualities are blended in the nature of every human being, among them each quality takes precedence over others in each individual and sometimes different qualities manifest themselves at different times in the same individual. When the “Sattvik” nature becomes predominant, man’s mind turns in the direction of the inner self. That is the auspicious moment. The same thing is Dharma. Dharma is that which is holding together and bearing everything. That which is the support and foundation for the living and the world – that which is wearing and bearing the self that is Dharma, which means the supreme, ultimate, absolute reality or God. Thus, that kind of living which follows the remembrance of Parameswara, the Supreme Lord is Dharma. That is Dharma which makes a man turn towards the self instead of moving away from its Realization.

It is not possible for the occurrence of “Sattva” never to happen ever in the life-span of any man some day, some moment. On account of some event in the world, in every human being there will arise the “sattva” quality in every man. That very moment is his moment of realization. If he wakes up to it then, he will know the path of good. When once he realizes the true nature what is good, it will be easy for him to distinguish between priorities of values. For one who has come to know the steps of values, determining the moral foundations is not difficult.

The means by which we know he differences between what the relative importance of things are, is the intellect. When “Sattva” springs forth what he has to be careful about is in matters of mind. The function of the mind is to determine through its intellectual function what is proper and what is improper. When it happens as a result of the thinking mind, it becomes the light of life’s progress.

The intellect is like a bridge connecting the external world and the inner self. It is a rope bridge. The hands that tug at them are the states of Rajas and Tamas. When “sattva” pulls it, the mind turns in the direction of the self and it acts as a corrective to the involvement with the world. That is culture. When Rajas and Tamas pull at it, the intellect turns towards the world and becomes a slave to the emotion of love, hatred and illusion. That is nature.

The individual free – will consists of making the mind stay put in “sattva” and preventing it from succumbing to Rajas and Tamas. If man doesn’t have that free-will, he may lose his capacity for personal responsibility in his actions. If all events in life are controlled by nature, if everything is pre-determined and man is not born free, if his own willed actions have no scope, then he cannot be subject to “Punya” (spiritual merit) and “Papa” (sin). Burdening a man who is not “free” with the fruits of actions is not just. Nature herself would have located personal freedom within man himself. That is why he has the responsibility of Papa and Punya. That is why it is inevitable for him to accept the fruits of his action.

When the intellect performs its function with inner sanction, man’s attitude to the world gets transformed in two ways – (1) Behaving towards others as he would behave towards himself, he is himself the measure for others. (2) The discrimination of what is more wealthy and what is less so.

He becomes capable of recognizing that the same life- force that is within him is what is within all living beings and the others are really oneself.
He will be constantly correcting himself by observing the high and the low in the world and the desires and intentions of his will be subject to the critical examination of his discriminatory weapon. In his achievement of the goals of life – especially the well known four fold-objects, in the case of the first three, namely, Dharma, Artha and Kama he will have an order of fixed priorities to attain Moksha.

-Apasthamba Dharmasutra II, 8, 20, 17-23.

[Engaging oneself in earning money in a way in which it is not detrimental to the path of Dharma, spending it in helping the deserving and in philanthropic acts, earning the good-will of the people, enjoying the pleasures of life which are not contrary to the injunctions of Dharma – a man who engages himself thus will win acclaim in both the worlds.]

-Mahabharata Udyogaparva. 124-38.

[A man who wants happiness and money must act according to Dharma. Money and happiness are not apart from Dharma. Therefore for the benefit of all three, Dharma is the means.]

-Mahabharata. Shantiparva. 197-8, 6

[of the Gunas, Dharma is the highest; earning money is the middle one; the lowest is the fulfillment of desires. A man who is dedicated to the Self must thus act according to putting Dharma first: he has to behave towards all living beings in the same way as he does with himself.]

In the case of a person who acts according to the principle “Atmavat Sarvabhuteshu” (seeing all beings as oneself) the qualities that bring peace of mind such as compassion towards all living things in daily life, generosity, fraternal feeling, kindness, eschewing of cruelty, not behaving with highhandedness, politeness, pleasantness, humility – these qualities are the natural by-products. He experiences pain in the pain of others. He guesses their state of mind and with conscious effort he pushes away the sort of talk which might trouble them. Extending friendliness and gaiety becomes his very nature.

For a man who has seen the richness and objects of enjoyment of the world with the vantage point of the supremacy of the Self and has learnt their limits and uses, indifference towards many worldly things becomes easy. He is more ready for self-sacrifice. The fiend of covetousness cannot capture him. Excessive possessiveness and attachment to worldly objects cannot come near him. The possibility of this clashing with others is very rare. He searches for a way of reconciliation in a situation of the quarrel. This way also he becomes dear to the world.

Culture is that propriety resulting in a behaviour moulded by a policy of treating others as oneself and the priorities of wealth determined by discrimination. For dozens of complex questions like what is just in which situation; which is etiquette; who deserves respect; in whose case one should show displeasure; what is the extent of that expression; what sort of words should be employed in such a situation; where is silence called for; what sort of tone should be adopted while speaking; what gestures are to be used – for all such questions, the cultured man finds answers in no time at all. The sense of propriety comes to him automatically, quite naturally like breath to the nose. His limbs and mouth, like the mind and the intellect behind them are always under his control. It is this control of the senses which is self- control; it means keeping himself under all control. He is the truly cultured man in whose internal machinery the nuts and bolts are ship-shape and smoothly oiled. His knowledge of proprieties and priorities is the mark of culture.

For these various qualities of culture to develop and strengthen, a long-time effort and practice are necessary. Can the congenital quirks and dirt be discarded like removing the apparel? It is only by adhering for long and steadily – it is only by “tapas” (concentrated meditation) that it is possible. That achievement of the principle cannot be completed only through conscious intellect. The whole mind should co-operate with it: The mind is more potent than mere intellect in its effect. The intellect works by fits and starts. But the mind is always active within us. Desire, pride, anger, vanity, envy, sorrow – all such aberrations are generated by the mind. Therefore the man desirous of culture should first of all clean up the mind or cultivating fine art and the company of cultivated people. That is the reason why usually, people believe that culture means music and literature, myths and legends. In actual fact, poetry, music, dancing and painting are not the entire body of culture; they are only some parts of it. The inner transformation effected by those form the necessary pre-requisites for culture.

Man’s mind gets purified by the great influence of the works of art. It acquires finesse as well as nobility. It will be composed of a feeling of general good for the world. Ramayana and the Mahabharata bring us experiences of life not easily available; As a result of this our inner vision gets refined; our area of interest gets enlarged. The goal of life gets ennobled. This maturity of life – awareness is the ultimate use of good literature. Similarly, the company of good people brings us great experiences and extremely sophisticated ones too. Thus the man who has refined himself by the study of art, by contact with society, by good company and by realizing the universality of the Self – such is the man exemplifying what the Bhagawadgita describes.

Culture

If an object in nature is beautified by the discrimination of man, it is culture.

The forest paddy is nature. The fine variety of grain of Pattisomana halli is culture. Paddy is nature; Rice is culture. Rice is nature: the cooked and refined sweet and sour variety of it is culture. A boulder is nature; the dressed stone in one’s courtyard is culture; the marble is nature, the statue carved out of it by a sculptor is culture. A lump of lumber is nature; table and chair are culture. The sounds produced by animals and birds is nature. Recognizing their melodic and tonal variations arranging them and organizing them into various ragas (the up and down scales of tones) is culture.

It seems the main characteristics of the seven swaras (the octave), Sa, Ri, Ga, Ma, Pa, Dha, Ni – are as follows:

-Amarakosha 1.8

[The utterance of a peacock is “Shadja”, that of a bull is “Rishabha”; that of a goat is “Gandhara” that of the Krauncha bird is “Madhyama”; that of the Cuckoo, the Indian koel is “Panchama”; that of the horse is “Dhaivata”; that of the elephant is “Nishada”.]

The words we talk and hear are nature – “Prakriti”; the same words arranged according to a meaningful pattern is culture – “Samskriti”. The urge to talk is nature. The limits and good manners in that are culture. Making water and relieving, this is nature. The donkey and the ox do not discriminate where they do it. The babies in the cradle don’t discriminate either. As the child grows it gets the sense of place and time. That is culture. That which happens consciously over and above what happens naturally is culture; if something stays the same as it was at its birth, it is nature, civilization is culture. It is nature when different kinds of flowers and leaves in a variety of colours shine forth. When they are gathered and made into a garland or a bouquet, it is culture. Mother Nature provides us with the raw materials for our livelihood. We use it in a proper context to yield meaning to our lives. That is culture. To convert a forest into a garden is culture. To comb it neatly, weave it into an artistic braid and decorate it with flowers is culture. That which has come into existence by itself is nature. When man tames into an intellectual order is culture. The various kinds of hungers of our body are nature. The orderly and meaningful way these are appeared according to the proper time, place and manner is culture.

Culture is not confined merely to a pleasing appearance and beautiful speech. That is external culture. Superior to that is inner, innate culture. Desires and emotional involvements are nature. A sense of justice and discrimination is culture. Anger and envy are nature; forgiveness and tolerance are culture. Thus in matters of mind, body speech, there is room for culture. Culture reaches its pinnacle in the mind’s nobility. When there is nobility in the mind, when there is beauty there – that nobility and beauty finds its external manifestation in our voice, speech, facial expression and courtesy in our behaviour.

Then two things happen:

Firstly, happiness takes place in the hearts of those with whom we are dealing with. They become pleased and turn out to be our allies.

Secondly if they have any narrow mindedness and ulterior motive, it comes down and they will also be capable of getting a glimpse or our superior ideal.

Thus there is a two-fold advantage. When culture enters into a mutual life-relationship, it brings friendship and happiness on both sides. In this programme, two things will have to take place:

First – Acquaintance with another’s nature. Second – Education of one’s own nature.

We will have to learn to the maximum extent possible the workings of another person’s mind and temperament and character. And, we have to make an adjustment to their mentality our own attitude to life. Thus the process of an individual making a friendly adjustment and correcting oneself suitably many be called culture.

The Story of the Cow

Well, what does one person adjusting himself to another exactly mean? In our story of the cow, does the cow adjust itself to the wishes of the tiger? Or, does the tiger become obedient to Punyakoti the cow? A tiger catching hold of a cow and eating it is natural, that is nature. The tiger admiring of truthfulness of the cow is culture. The cow confessing about the calf is culture. The tiger responding and showing sympathy is a cultural response. The culture residing in the cow became the cause for the culture in the tiger.

It has already been suggested that when culture reaches its summit, it becomes the principle for the establishment of a relationship between two lives. What is “life”? It is the combination of two objects; one part of it is the conglomorations of the body and the sense organs; the other is the self or the soul. The sense organ desires the comforts of the world; the soul hankers after a consciousness higher than itself. Culture has got both these aspects in view; Worldly comfort and elevation of the soul.

There is a common feeling among men that both these are mutually opposed to each other. It is the conceptual belief of culture that they are not opposed to each other but are complementary and helpful. They are like two steps; it is not possible to ascend the second step without ascending the first. The first step was useless unless the second was ascended. There is a place for both steps in a man’s life. When once it is accepted that in an animal called man the most paramount thing is an element called Self, it becomes proper for all other aspects of life the basics of the substratum for the attainment of that Supreme Goal. There are a thousand things we want in life. Among them there are some which are of lasting value, and some which are momentary enjoyment. Each one of them has its own proper place. It has its value in that specific place. In other places, it appears undesirable. The delicious sweet rice, instead of falling into the mouth falls on the thigh or lap it is disgusting. In keeping with this, there is a saying in English. A thing out of its place is dirt. That object which leaves its own deserved place and places itself in another is dirt. This same principle can be applied to administrative matters also. A police constable can arrest a guilty person and present him before a magistrate. That is his duty. But if he exceeds his jurisdictory duty and conducts a trial himself and awards a sentence, then it is dirt. Similarly if a magistrate himself sets out to arrest a culprit, then it is dirt. To search for and bring an outlaw to justice is a policeman’s duty, not the magistrate’s. Thus each position or office has its own limits. Knowing these limits and giving each thing the value it deserves is justice. Justice itself is culture.

Thus assigning each object in the world its proper place is the job of culture. Determing the importance of each place is also the province of culture. All in all, the propriety of our actions itself is culture. There are two principles to this propriety –

(1) The Self I supreme. Therefore it deserves universal respect; (2) Because the Self is found in everyone as it is found in me and in the same way, I must value the sorrow and joys of others the same way as I value them in me. Thus if I owe a duty and responsibility to others, along with it, it becomes incumbent on my part to know their feelings and desires. Thus knowing what others feel becomes a part of culture. First the knowledge of their expectations; then propriety of behaviour as a consequence of it.

Of the various aspects of man, isn’t the self the highest? The Self is the same in everybody. Therefore superiority and inferiority don’t exist in the matter of the supreme Self. But worldly things are not like that. There, depending on the differences in their intelligence and mind, the values of things change. For one man eating is important; for another, looks. One man prefers a round face; another an oval one; one man likes sweets; another hot and pungent stuff. One lady prefers jasmine; another champak. One woman likes apparel; another music. One man gets angry soon and also forgets it soon. Another man takes a long time to get angry and doesn’t forget it even after twelve years. One man is trusting and doesn’t think for himself. Another cannot trust anyone and he thinks too much. Thus in mankind, there are dozens of varieties of mentalities, intellectual abilities and moral outlooks and these are found in various levels. A cultured man understands these levels and adjusts his talk and behaviour to the situation on hand. No matter what the circumstance, his endeavour is for creating wellbeing.

Here we must notice that what is good is different from what brings happiness. There are moments when they both get together, there are moments when they stand apart. For a drunkard drinking brings happiness, it is not good. For a sick child sweets bring happiness, but not good. For a sick manmedicine is good but it does not bring happiness. For an uneducated boy freedom is happiness but it is not good.

For a sick man honey is good as well as cause for happiness. For a good student a time schedule is good as well as beneficial.

Happiness satisfies the senses first. After cogitation whether it is good or bad is known to the intellect. What is beneficial is first cognized by the mind. Afterwards, even if the experience does not bring happiness to the mind, we receive it willingly. A beautiful girl who loves to decorate herself with ornaments suffers the pain of getting her ears pierced receives it as desirable. Such is the nature of what is good. That which is received by the thoughtful discrimination is good. That is good which is approved by the self as such. That comfort which does not impede personal good is happiness.

The means and the case which shows us with example the various modes of understanding others’ minds and that which makes clear to our minds the sophisticated emotions in literature like poetry and drama, that which educates our intellect – this role is performed by the fine arts like music, stage presentation through acting, sculpture and painting. Thus the literary arts are the feeding elements for culture. In the Ramayana and the Mahabharata we can see plenty of examples of cultured behaviour.

(1) When Sri Ramachandra and Lakshmana armed themselves with bows, arrows and swords and started to go to the forest, Sitadevi addressed her husband thus “My lord, when fighting weapons are in one’s arms, they are capable of engendering a cruel frame of mind, there is the fear that innocent people might come to harm form you”. After giving this warning and after mentioning an incident in such a circumstance, she adds at the end: “Lord, I have not spoken to teach you something you don’t know; the love and respect I have for you have made me remind you of your own opinion”.

Sita spoke Dharma. To whom? To the very personification of all Dharma Therefore, in addition to packing the thoughts of Dharma, she imparted humble politeness. This is propriety.

(2) At the Kurukshetra the armies of the Pandavas and the Kauravas are gathered ready for battle. When everyone was in the middle of that enthusiastic expectancy, Dharmaraya got off from his chariot and walked barefoot towards the enemy camp. His brothers and friends mistakenly thought that out of fear he was walking across to surrender and tried to prevent him. What did he do? He went to Acharya Bhishma and said –

Yudhishtira held both the feet of Bhishmacharya and said “Sir, nobody can vanquish you. We have come to wage war with you. For that purpose, I have approached you to beg you. Please give us permission; Please bless us.”

This is the way of culture. Bhishma, after making it clear to Dharmaraya that it would have been wrong had he not done so, blessed him.

It is said that culture is one of those inexplicable things containing the wealth of thought, speech and action, all combined, though it is beyond description, it is not beyond cognition. Everybody is able to recognize it the moment they come across it as a special attraction. The path of culture is not fraught with roughness and obstinacy; it is a path of smoothness and politeness. What is the difference between a life without grace and finesse and that of dog which rushes forward to grab the leftovers?